<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A golden topaze, or, Heart-jewell namely, a conscience purified and pacified by the blood and spirit of Christ / written by Francis Whiddon ...</title>
            <author>Whiddon, Francis, d. 1656 or 7.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11990456</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11990456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 829:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A golden topaze, or, Heart-jewell namely, a conscience purified and pacified by the blood and spirit of Christ / written by Francis Whiddon ...</title>
                  <author>Whiddon, Francis, d. 1656 or 7.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 140 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peace of mind.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Golden Topaze, OR, Heart-jewell. Namely, A Conſcience purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pacified by the Blood and Spirit of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written</hi> by FRANCIS WHIDDON <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Morton-Hampſted <hi>in</hi> Devon.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Unicnique liber eſſe propria Conſcientia, &amp; ad hunc librum diſcutiendum, &amp; emendandum omnes alii inventi ſunt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Bernard.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hall. 1656.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:2"/>
            <head>TO MY FAITHFULL Flock, who love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in Sincerity. Mercy unto you, and peace, and love be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Deare Children,</hi> for ſo I am bold to call you, <hi>though you have had many teachers, yet not many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; if</hi> I may credit your owne tongues, there is a number of you will ſay, that <hi>in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus I have begotten you through the Goſpell,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.15. Let God have the glory: for <hi>what is Paul? or what is Apollos:</hi> or what am I? But the <hi>weake Inſtrument</hi> by whom the <hi>all-ſufficient God</hi> hath wrought <hi>faith in your hearts.</hi> I therefore according unto my
<pb facs="tcp:52020:3"/>Duty do here preſent unto you a tender of my true Affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you; in this plaine and ſhort Tract of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> The <hi>ſubject</hi> is worthy of all Acceptation, Though the <hi>Author</hi> bee the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of all his Brethren. You may conſider it as an Object both to your eare and eye, your <hi>eare</hi> hath heard it preached, and your <hi>eye</hi> may ſee and read it, and if your <hi>heart</hi> Affect it, the <hi>Jewell</hi> is your owne. And I who am your Paſtor may take the Boldneſſe and ſay. <hi>I need no Epiſtle of Commendation to you, or Epiſtle of Commendation from you: you are mine Epiſtle knowne and read of all that have ſpirituall eyes,</hi> and are acquainted with you, yea, <hi>you are the Epiſtle of Chriſt written not with Inke, but with the ſpirit, Not in Tables of ſtone, but in the
<pb facs="tcp:52020:3"/>fleſhy Tables of the heart.</hi> I hope I ſhall not be aſhamed of this my <hi>fooliſh Boaſting,</hi> But that when I am gone from you, this pretious <hi>Jewell</hi> which now I preſent unto you, will then be found ſtill to abide within you, and if at any time through careleſneſſe, <hi>this Jewell of a good Conſcience</hi> with in you, ſhall gather Duſt and loſe it's luſtre: Let this little Tract, if better be wanting, be Aſſumed by you, Read it once and againe <hi>humbly</hi> and <hi>adviſedly,</hi> ſo may you have hope, that your Dull and Dusky <hi>Conſciences</hi> will <hi>Recover it's</hi> former luſtre, with more peace and Purity.</p>
            <p>And Now my <hi>deare children,</hi> knowing that ſhortly I muſt <hi>put off this my tabernacle of Fleſh,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.14. and be brought to the <hi>houſe appointed for all living,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:52020:4"/>Job. 30.23. I ſhall endeavour to give you ſome few Advertiſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts before I <hi>goe hence and be ſeene, no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know (<hi>Deare ſoules</hi>) we are the people <hi>on whom the ends of the world are Come, and our daies very perilous and Dangerous,</hi> as ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3, 4. In which we find <hi>Iniquite</hi> to <hi>Abound</hi> and <hi>Damnable Errors</hi> &amp; Hereſies to <hi>Superabound.</hi> What Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall fancy, what Anti-Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall opinions? What Immaginary Raptures and Revelations have we now Amongſt us? ſo that now to <hi>Refraine from their</hi> evill <hi>opinion</hi> and <hi>practiſes,</hi> is to <hi>make our ſelves a prey.</hi> Never were the <hi>times</hi> more Contagious; <hi>Opinions</hi> more Infectious, &amp; <hi>practiſes</hi> more Dangerous. So that every pious ſoule had need to be a Spirituall
<pb facs="tcp:52020:4"/>Phyſician, and ſtill to have <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials</hi> to fortifie his ſoule <hi>within,</hi> and <hi>Repercuſſives</hi> to beate back the Infectious Venome of Sin and Error without. <hi>Preſervatives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Be conſtant and ſincere in the preformance of all holy Duties, both <hi>publike</hi> and <hi>private</hi> in the <hi>Congregation</hi> and the <hi>Family. Let your holineſse appeare unto all,</hi> Be holy abroad and at home. Deſpiſe not ordinances neither in whole or part. But receive them with all thankfulneſſe as Love-tokens from your Father, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg a Neceſſitie of them all, and that as long as you are <hi>Below Temptations,</hi> you cannot be <hi>above</hi> Ordinances, which will be as long as you carry your Fraile <hi>Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> about you. They are <hi>more neceſſary then your Appointed food; More to be Deſired then Gold, yea
<pb facs="tcp:52020:5"/>then fine Gold; And ſincere milke ſweeter then the hony or hony Comb,</hi> without which, you cannot be nouriſhed up unto <hi>everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Keepe cloſe to your God in a way of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>prayſes.</hi> Be Conſtant in Both: <hi>pray alwaies and in all things give thankes.</hi> What Grace you want <hi>get</hi> it by <hi>Prayer,</hi> and what good you enjoy <hi>weare</hi> it By <hi>Prayſe.</hi> If you thus <hi>draw neare to God</hi> in a way of <hi>Duty</hi> God will be ſtill <hi>neare unto</hi> you in a way of <hi>Mercy.</hi> The leaſt Dropp of the wine of mercy, ſhould Inflame your <hi>hearts</hi> with true thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and fill your <hi>Mouths</hi> with conſtant prayſes. So that you lay new Ingagement on the <hi>god of mercy</hi> to beſtow more <hi>mercies;</hi> Not only to preſerve you from the <hi>evill of evils,</hi> But ever to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich
<pb facs="tcp:52020:5"/>you with the <hi>bleſsing of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Give not way to a cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Dulneſſe in Duty, but performe every Duty with all your power, with ſincere <hi>Intention,</hi> with heate of <hi>Affection,</hi> and with <hi>Diligence,</hi> and <hi>Delight.</hi> Eſpecially be not ſlight in <hi>ſecret prayer, meditation,</hi> and <hi>reading.</hi> Doe not the <hi>worke of the Lord deceitfully</hi> or negligently, leaſt the <hi>curſe</hi> of God fall on you, <hi>Jer:</hi> 48.10. <hi>Mal:</hi> 1.14. but zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly and heartily; <hi>watch to</hi> theſe duties, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. Keep your hearts in a good frame for them, undefiled with <hi>ſin,</hi> untainted with the <hi>world;</hi> Endeavour to feele all Duties at your hearts, inlivening, inlarging, and inflaming your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Lay not out the chiefe of your zeale on Externals, opinions, and the ſmaller things of Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:52020:6"/>but let <hi>ſoule-ſaving worke</hi> be your maine and daily imployment. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe your ſelves in <hi>ſelfe-examination,</hi> looke daiely into your owne boſomes by a ſerious ſcruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſpare not thoſe beloved <hi>Dalilah's,</hi> and curſed <hi>Achans</hi> which are the <hi>troublers of our Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Get true light in your Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, not only a <hi>ſpeculative,</hi> but <hi>ſpirituall light;</hi> not a <hi>notionall,</hi> but <hi>experimentall</hi> light, <hi>the light of the knowledge of God in the face of Jeſus.</hi> Such a light whereby you may be inabled to ſee <hi>ſin</hi> to be the <hi>greateſt evill,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> himſelfe to be the <hi>cheifeſt good.</hi> Such a light that melts the ſoule, that humbles the ſoule, that enlivens the ſoule, that quickens the ſoule, and that quiets the ſoule. Nouriſh not an <hi>head-light,</hi> but an <hi>heart-light.</hi> Let <hi>the word of truth dwell in you plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:52020:6"/>Weake judgments are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſled both in opinion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, but a ſound judgement will preſerve you in both. So <hi>fly</hi> one error that you do not <hi>fall</hi> into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; it is eaſy to run into <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames,</hi> but very difficult to keep the <hi>golden Meane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Keep your hearts with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi> (4. Pro.) Watch daily to prevent him, which watcheth ever to miſcheife you, I <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. And let yours praiers be frequent and fervent, <hi>Lord lead us not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> Your enemies are <hi>many, mighty,</hi> and <hi>malicious,</hi> which ſtill lye in waite to breake your <hi>peace,</hi> wound your <hi>conſciences,</hi> leſſen your <hi>comforts,</hi> impaire your <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> blurre your <hi>evidences,</hi> and dampe your <hi>aſſurances;</hi> and unleſſe you ſtand upon your Guard, &amp; ſet your ſelves in <hi>battell-array,</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:52020:7"/>fight with thoſe ſtrong, ſubtile, ſedulous <hi>Goliahs,</hi> which come out to <hi>upbraid</hi> Gods little <hi>Champion.</hi> They (I meane the Divell and his Agents, viz: the world and the fleſh) will not only <hi>rage</hi> but <hi>raigne;</hi> not only aſſault, but take your ſoules <hi>captive</hi> at their will. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as you love your owne ſoules and the welfare of them unto all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity) <hi>Get unto you the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God. Eph. 6. 13. Be ſtrong in the Lord and in the power of his might.</hi> Give no faire <hi>Quarter</hi> unto foule <hi>tempations:</hi> make up ſpeedily every Breach between God and your owne <hi>conſciences,</hi> and let not <hi>conſcience</hi> looſe its Tenderneſſe, but ſhun every evill and the <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let thy life be the life of <hi>faith.</hi> Saith <hi>Paul, the life that we now live in the fleſh, we live by the
<pb facs="tcp:52020:7"/>faith of the Son of God, who loved us, and gave himſelfe for us.</hi> Keep freſh the ſenſe of his love, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies acknowledge a continuall need of his <hi>Bloud, Spirit,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsion,</hi> and how much you are beholding and ingaged unto him. Labour to draw and derive from Chriſt by the powerfull attractive force of <hi>faith,</hi> ſpirituall ability, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for every dayes worke. Act your faith dayly in the promiſes of grace and ſtrength. Go unto Chriſt ſtill for his <hi>wiſdome</hi> to counſell you; for his <hi>righteousſneſs</hi> to cover you, for <hi>ſtrength</hi> to reſiſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for the <hi>ſhoulder</hi> that muſt beare our Croſſes; for <hi>ability</hi> to performe all duties as duties.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Reſolve with david <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101. that you will <hi>not know a wicked perſon</hi> (i.e.) approve of him. If <hi>out</hi> of your families, have not fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:52020:8"/>with them, but <hi>reprove</hi> them; if in your families, let them not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide within your doores, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him or her as perſons moſt infectious and dangerous. We have ſins enough and too too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our owne, therefore let us not encreaſe them by a baſe conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency at others mens ſins. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally avoid that generation of men whoſe grand deſigne it is to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to ruine the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> and to robb them of that <hi>maintenance,</hi> which is due unto them by the <hi>law of God,</hi> and by the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and by the <hi>law of Nations.</hi> Theſe <hi>croaking frogges</hi> have overſpread our <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ſo that they have made it <hi>ſtinke</hi> with their damnable Opinions &amp; devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh practiſes. <hi>They creep into hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and lead aſide ſilly women, 2 Tim. 3.11. and by their faire ſpeeches
<pb facs="tcp:52020:8"/>deceive the hearts of the ſimple, Rom.</hi> 16.18. And ſhall, <hi>if it were poſsible, deceive the very elect, Mark</hi> 13.22.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Affect a faithfull and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſter, who doth carefully look both to <hi>himſelfe</hi> and <hi>his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> Adſcribe neither too much, nor too little to your <hi>Teachers.</hi> Neither <hi>deſpiſe</hi> them, nor <hi>deify</hi> them, as the manner of ſome is. Eſteeme him not as a <hi>principle Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> but as a <hi>ſubordinate Actor;</hi> not as a <hi>Lord,</hi> but a <hi>Steward;</hi> not as a <hi>Maſter,</hi> but a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and yet account him more then an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Servant, even a man of God, <hi>A ſervant of the moſt high God,</hi> that ſheweth you the way of Salvation. Look on him not only as a <hi>Seer,</hi> but <hi>Over-ſeer,</hi> a <hi>Steward</hi> of Gods high ſecrets, a <hi>meſſenger</hi> of the Lord of Hoſtes, by whoſe Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb facs="tcp:52020:9"/>peace is concluded, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation miniſterially made up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man. He is <hi>Gods mouth to you</hi> by preaching, and <hi>your mouth to God</hi> by praying. On that in ſpeciall place ſtandeth before God, and miniſtreth to him upon <hi>earth, as the Angels do it in heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Woodnots Aphoriſms</hi> 1. <hi>Cens. p.</hi> 42. The Jewes ſay, that he that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Rabbi, ſhall never be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this world, nor in the world to come. i.e. of <hi>his tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher that hath the charge of his ſoule.</hi>
               </note> Therefore take heed you fall not out with your <hi>Teacher,</hi> whome the moſt wiſe God hath thought fit to make your <hi>Paſtor; forſake not the Levite as long as thou liveſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth,</hi> Deut. 12.19. Doe not deſire ſuch a Teacher as thou mayeſt <hi>rule him,</hi> but ſuch as may <hi>rule you, Magiſtrates</hi> are choſen to governe the people, not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to governe them. So <hi>Miniſters</hi> you are not to command them but obey them. Therefore <hi>obey them that have the Rule over you,</hi> Heb. 13.17. <hi>And ſubmit your ſelves, for
<pb facs="tcp:52020:9"/>they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account, that they may do it with Joy and not with greife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt, let <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> poſſeſſe your moſt ſerious thoughts, waite for the one, and provide for the other. <hi>Dye daiely,</hi> (with Paul) and you ſhall dye well. Have thine end ever in thine eye, and ſweeten the bitter cup of <hi>Death</hi> by a dayly preparation. Get your tackling all in readineſſe, that you may faile over the Sea of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <hi>miſeries</hi> in ſafety and ſecurity to the Port of <hi>happineſſe.</hi> You ſhall all of you ere long lye gaſping for death on your dying beds, and there lye grappling with the <hi>King of feares,</hi> attended with Terrors. Therefore (as you love your ſoules) let the whole courſe of your lives be a conſcionable preparative
<pb facs="tcp:52020:10"/>to dye comfortably. Look on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day as your laſt. So live that you may ſay with <hi>David, Though I walke through the Valley of the ſhaddow of death, I will not feare.</hi> Oh that you would be <hi>wiſe and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your latter end,</hi> before you go downe to the <hi>chambers of death, whence you ſhall never returne.</hi> Would you dye <hi>willingly?</hi> would you dye <hi>well?</hi> Then get a part in Chriſt, a Title to him, an Intereſt in him. <hi>Worke out your ſalvation with feare and trembling. Give all diligence to make your calling and election ſure.</hi> So live, that you may not be aſhamed to die. So <hi>number your dayes, that you may apply your hearts to true wiſdome.</hi> So caſt up your <hi>Accounts, that you may give them up with joy and not with greife. Judge your ſelves</hi> for your daiely Deviations, and you <hi>ſhall not be
<pb facs="tcp:52020:11"/>judged; condemne your ſelves, and you ſhall not be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 Laſtly. Let this little Book be in your hands, heads, and hearts. Let a <hi>good conſcience</hi> be written on your ſoules with <hi>Characters inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> never to be razed out, ſo that when death ſhall appeare, thou mayeſt be able to ſay, <hi>I have lived in all good conſcience before God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whereas dull ſpirits are more quickned by <hi>Examples</hi> then <hi>Precepts.</hi> This place hath had a great advantage above other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces adjacent. Mr. <hi>John Southmead</hi> who is now a glorious Saint in heaven, and his Soule made <hi>happy with the Spirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> You know he was an old Diſciple, and ſerved his Maſter faithfully in his generation for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares, zealouſly ſtriving for
<pb facs="tcp:52020:12"/>the inlargment of the <hi>Kingdome of Chriſt</hi> and demoliſhing the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Satan.</hi> A great Curb he was to prophaneſſe, witneſſe his great paines and travell in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing thoſe Heatheniſh ſports and paſtimes, which were too common even upon the <hi>Lords day.</hi> God made him the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to aboliſh <hi>Wakes, Revells, Maypoles</hi> and <hi>May-games,</hi> with their Apurtenances, <hi>Fidlers</hi> and <hi>ſuperfluous Ale-houſes,</hi> not only in his owne, but in many other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes adjacent. So that not only the Practice, but even the Name of theſe ſinfull Vanities is almoſt forgotten. Againe, as he was a ſtrong Curb to prophaneſſe, ſo was he as ſharp a ſpurr unto holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Witneſſe his great coſt and paines in getting a faithfull Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to inſtruct the people. Very
<pb facs="tcp:52020:10"/>carefull abroad to <hi>warne the unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to comfort the feeble minded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>and to ſupport the weake.</hi> And at home in his Family in repeating Sermons; reading, opening, and applying Scriptures unto ſuch as were under him; conſtantly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a Bleſſing on them, and as carefull in returning Praiſe to God for every Bleſſing both publick and private. But at laſt when the <hi>evill dayes came on him, ſo that the Keepers of the houſe began to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 14.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>the ſtrong man to bow, the grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ceaſe, and the windowes to be darkened,</hi> he was willing for a Deſolution, very ready to goe hence, often ſaying, <hi>It is time for mee to be gone, my Maſter hath no more worke for me to do here upon earth.</hi> Now ſhall we forget ſuch a worthy <hi>ſervant of God?</hi> by no meanes. Let his <hi>memory</hi> be ever
<pb facs="tcp:52020:11"/>
               <hi>bleſſed,</hi> and his <hi>Name as precious oyntment powred forth.</hi> And let us honour his remembrance in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitation of his vertues. But ſhould we forget him, yet his God would not forget his place, his perſon, his zeale, his labour of love: <hi>The Lord ſhall count when he writeth up his people, that this man was borne there. Pſ.</hi> 87.6. even in the <hi>family</hi> of <hi>Wrey,</hi> within the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of Morton,</hi> and in the <hi>County of Devon.</hi> Now you having ſuch an excellent Patterne and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, let it be your earneſt deſire and endeavour to <hi>run on and not be weary, walke on and not be faint</hi> in thoſe waies (paved ith holineſſe) in which he hath walked, that ſo your <hi>end may be everlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, looke on this <hi>ſmall Tract</hi> as a <hi>Dowry</hi> which your <hi>dying</hi> Paſtor hath bequeathed unto you,
<pb facs="tcp:52020:13"/>whom he <hi>loves in the Lord.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this proviſion which he hath made for you of wholſome meat, not caring for concealed Cookery, or the <hi>vaine enticing words of mans wiſdome.</hi> As it was intended for your <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> delivered to your <hi>Attention;</hi> ſo let it be digeſted by your <hi>Meditation,</hi> and practiſed in your <hi>Converſation.</hi> So both <hi>Paſtor</hi> and <hi>People</hi> ſhall behold each others face with joy at the <hi>Barr</hi> of Chriſt; and have a moſt happy admiſſion into his moſt glorious <hi>preſence, where there is fulneſſe of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate though unworthy Teacher, FRANCIS WHIDDON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:12"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is preſented unto thine eye <hi>a little ſmall Tract,</hi> which in it's front doth promiſe great things, as <hi>precious Stones</hi> and <hi>Jewels:</hi> Poſsibly if thou with an humble heart ſhalt <hi>call</hi> and <hi>cry, ſeek</hi> and <hi>ſearch,</hi> thou mayeſt find that which will be better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Gold, more excellent then refined Silver,</hi> namely a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi> Let not any prejudice of <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>partes</hi> cauſe thee to caſt it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, as not worthy thy view, neither cry thou, Tuſh what is this <hi>Pamphlet</hi> unto thoſe many large and learned <hi>Volumes</hi> of thoſe able and holy men, that have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erly written upon this ſubject. I doe ingenuouſly confeſſe, it is very meane, my <hi>vintage</hi> leſſe then others <hi>gleanings.</hi> But what of that; if thou be an humble Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; thou wilt acknowledge that <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:52020:13"/>and <hi>Apollos</hi> are but iuſtruments, and can do nothing without their principall Efficient, alſo we find by dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the leſſe of <hi>man,</hi> the more of <hi>God;</hi> he can worke as well by the weakeſt as ableſt inſtrument, &amp; draw as ſtrongly with an hair, as with a Cable rope. I muſt acknowledge the diſcourſe is very ſhort and very plaine, and both very needfull: in theſe full and ſurfeiting times; who ſeeth not that great volumes are little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, &amp; large diſcourſes are eaſily laid aſide: men find much <hi>reading to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome to the fleſh,</hi> I therefore affect <hi>brevity</hi> with <hi>perſpicuity.</hi> Should I be long in my diſcourſe, I am confident thou wouldeſt not read it over. But in ſo much as it is very ſhort, an houres labour or ſo; I may have hopes that thou wilt read it over and over, and the oftner the better.</p>
            <p>As for plaineneſſe of the ſtile, I would have thee to know the <hi>Author</hi> is a very plaine man, and hath written it for a
<pb facs="tcp:52020:14"/>very plaine people in his owne Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. This was never intended to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the world, but to be confined to the <hi>place</hi> and <hi>people</hi> where it was firſt <hi>preached;</hi> a people that deſire the <hi>plaine evidence of the Spirit,</hi> &amp; <hi>not the vaine enticing words of mans wiſdome.</hi> Therefore if thy Braine run over with vain ſpeculations, high notions, &amp; frothy expreſsions, and wilt be <hi>wiſe above what is written, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>4.6.</hi> remember that of <hi>Auſtin, Multi propter arborem ſcientiae amittunt arborem vitae.</hi> Many with <hi>Adam</hi> ſo eagerly ſtrive for the tree of knowledge, that they loſe the tree of life. A good caveat for ſuch as are all for <hi>new diſcoveries, new lights,</hi> but not <hi>new lives.</hi> To you therefore that with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian</hi> cry, <hi>quid novi?</hi> what new thing? I muſt anſwer, <hi>nec nova, nec novè,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</note> here is nothing new, but <hi>vetus veritas iiſdem verbis &amp; iiſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyllabis. The old truth in its owne words and ſyllables.</hi> If this
<pb facs="tcp:52020:15"/>do not like you, then lay it gently aſide, and it will not harme you.</p>
            <p>But unto you that heartily deſire to <hi>have</hi> and to <hi>hold,</hi> to <hi>uſe</hi> and exerciſe, alwaies, in all things, and to all perſons, <hi>a Conſcience void of offence:</hi> if you want better helps take this for preſent. And becauſe this little Book muſt with little <hi>Benjamin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 43.14</note> be ſent into <hi>Egypt,</hi> I ſhall with <hi>old Jacob,</hi> deſire that it may find <hi>favour</hi> where it comes. If others deſire the like with mee; I hope that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they in <hi>Reading,</hi> nor I in <hi>Writing</hi> ſhall loſe our labour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine as thou art Chriſt's</hi> F.W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 11. 1656. Imprimatur GERARD LANGBAINE Pro-Vicecan. OXON.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52020:15"/>
            <head>The TOPAZ.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 13.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For we truſt we have a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Willing in all things to live honeſtly.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Find it reported of Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> long ſince that a great deſire poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed him of hearing <hi>Paul</hi> to Preach.</p>
            <p>Another like affected with him, ſeconds his deſire with this of his own: which was, that his Theam or Text might be <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe good men were friends to <hi>Conſcience,</hi> they ſaw how the Cauſe ſtood with her, namely that ſhe was in a languiſhing condition, and ready to die: what their thoughts were we can onely gueſſe: but in theſe dayes of ours, theſe laſt and worſt dayes, if we ponder the wayes and workes, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and practiſes of the moſt, we have juſt cauſe to complaine, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52020:16"/>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not onely ſick and dying, but dead and buried in the <hi>grave</hi> of habituall ſin, with the <hi>ſtone</hi> of hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe rolled on the grave, and that ſhe hath laid ſo long in the duſt of oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that her name is become unſavory, &amp; the very mentioning of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is nauſeated by every <hi>prophane Beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's high time, therefore, to crave the help of an Angel, yea the <hi>Angel of the Covenant</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour; <hi>to roll away the ſtone,</hi> and to raiſe up our dead friend <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as ſometimes he raiſed up his dead friend <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This worke of raiſing the dead is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per unto God onely, yet may an omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God uſe impotent man in ſuch a worke; as <hi>Eliſha</hi> in raiſing the <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> dead ſon to life,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.34. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 40.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> in reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Eutychus,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>reviving Tabitha (aliàs) Dorcas.</hi> Now he that imployed men then, in raiſing dead bodies, can and will imploy men ſtill in raiſing dead ſoules, dead <hi>conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> who knoweth what God may do, if we do our parts? if the <hi>Hebrews
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52020:16"/>pray,</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul preach,</hi> and God come in with a <hi>bleſſing</hi> on both, what ſhall hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but that the dead <hi>conſcience</hi> ſhould be revived, the drowſie awakened, the weake confirmed, the troubled quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the good bettered, and every e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſoule returne to his reſt with ſome meaſure of <hi>Pauls</hi> conſidence, and ſay, I truſt I have a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in all things to live honeſtly?</p>
            <p>The occaſion of <hi>Pauls</hi> pleading a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> I find to be thus;<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Occaſion.</note> there were certaine ill-affected perſons among the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> who calumniated <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine,<note place="margin">Theophilact in h. l.</note> as tending to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> law; ſo that many, who had formerly given their <hi>Names</hi> to Chriſt began now to draw back from <hi>Paul</hi> as a <hi>Seducer</hi> and <hi>falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> and ſo their Affections alienated from him. He therefore (to cleare himſelfe from ſuch falſe aſperſions and calumniations, and to confirme and eſtabliſh the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> in the truth,) gives them to underſtand, that he had not dealt <hi>fallaciouſly,</hi> but <hi>faithfully</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52020:17"/>with them in what he had taught them: and therefore adviſeth them to continue conſtant in their obedience unto their Teachers, and in ſervent prayer unto God for them. For ſaith he, we are aſſured we have <hi>a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> willing in all things to live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly.</p>
            <p>You may terme this Text <hi>Pauls Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph,</hi> or his <hi>choice Jewel,</hi> with which the whole world compared and <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Ballance,</hi> will be found as light as droſſe and vanity, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, all things are but <hi>loſſe, dung, and vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1.<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Analyſis.</note> 
                  <hi>Pauls Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Pauls Conſidence.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt note the quality, it is a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond the propriety, it is <hi>his owne good Conſcience, I have a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> his confidence, you have 1. his Aſſurance, <hi>(we truſt)</hi> 2. the grounds of it built on foure firme pillars,
<list>
                  <item>1. His will, <hi>(deſiring.)</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52020:17"/>
                  <item>2. The Extent, <hi>(in all things.)</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The Conſtancy of his will, (<hi>to walke</hi> or live.)</item>
                  <item>4. The Syncerity of it, namely <hi>(ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.)</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of <hi>conſcience</hi> in generall; it would be very tedious to ſhew you the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men upon the definition of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> all varying in <hi>terme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Habitus multis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitionibus acquiſitus: Habitus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectualis, quâ talis, officium eſt unicum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinare ad promptè a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum; Conſcientia verò mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas habet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perationes, quas imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dtatè exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, ergo non Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Ames de Conſcien.</note> and ſome in <hi>truth.</hi> Much adoe there is amongſt Divines to find out the <hi>Genus</hi> or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall terme of it, as alſo the <hi>difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some calling it an <hi>act,</hi> ſome an <hi>habit,</hi> ſome a <hi>faculty,</hi> ſome a <hi>power.</hi> As for the two former, they are liable to juſt exception, that call it an <hi>act</hi> or <hi>habit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It cannot properly be called an <hi>act,</hi> becauſe <hi>conſcience</hi> many times doth not <hi>act,</hi> as in ſleepy men and <hi>ſeared conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It cannot be properly termed an <hi>habit,</hi> becauſe <hi>conſcience</hi> is innate, not acquired.</p>
            <p>The two latter, a <hi>faculty,</hi> or <hi>power,</hi> are generally imbraced, but eſpecially the laſt. Some leave out <hi>faculty,</hi> becauſe the Scripture hath not yet determined
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52020:18"/>it to be a <hi>diſtinct faculty,</hi> but calling it ſometimes the <hi>ſpirit of a man,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>ſpirit of the mind of man,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoid all exception, I ſhall pitch upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the laſt terme, namely <hi>power,</hi> as the true <hi>genus,</hi> and ſo define it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> is an inbred light in the mind of man, teaching him to follow what is good, and to eſchew that which is evill: and it is called <hi>conſcientia, quaſi concludens ſcientia;</hi> and it hath a two-fold Act, the firſt is to give Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to things, whether we have done well or ill; if we have done them well, then it giveth teſtimony for us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1. <hi>My Conſcience alſo bearing me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> and if we have done evill, then it teſtifieth againſt us. Therefore <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi> uſed to call the Conſcience <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animae;</hi> for as a Pedagogue wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon a Child, and commendeth him when he doth well, and on the contrary whippeth him when he doth evill; ſo the <hi>conſcience,</hi> when a man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, it ſtingeth him like <hi>Hornets, Deut.</hi> 7.20. But when he doth well, it allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, bids him go on, maugre all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52020:18"/>oppoſition, and to rejoice and ſing, though in a <hi>priſon</hi> with <hi>Peter,</hi> or in <hi>ſtocks</hi> with <hi>Paul. (vid. Weemſe divine exercitations.)</hi> But to define it more plainly and fully.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a Relative power in the reaſonable Creature,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Definition</note> which upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination through the light of Gods law, doth either excuſe or accuſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>power,</hi> becauſe of the many ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and workings which it dayly exerciſeth in us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Its a <hi>Relative power,</hi> not abſolute,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Conſcientia i.e. ſcientia cum alia ſcientia.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Cum Deo ſcire.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Cum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo ſcire.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſcire.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Cum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ipſis conſcire.</p>
               </note> becauſe what Conſcience doth, it doth it in Relation to another, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>conſcience,</hi> becauſe it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with another, with one that is of familiarity with it, and witneſſeth the truth with it, and this is God alone, who only knoweth the heart, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the reines. Hence it is that <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the <hi>ſpirit of God</hi> to ſecond his <hi>conſcience, I ſpeake the truth in Chriſt, I lie not, my Conſcience bearing me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the holy Ghoſt:</hi> where you may ſee 3 witneſſes produced by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and all of them without exception,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52020:19"/>namely Chriſt, the holy Ghoſt, and Conſcience, which is <hi>mille teſtes</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>ſubject</hi> in which <hi>conſcience</hi> is ſeated, it is in the reaſonable Creature, I doe not ſay it is in the Creatour, for God being holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe, needeth not Conſcience to order, governe and direct him. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I ſay it is in the unreaſonable creature, becauſe Beaſts and Fowles wanting reaſon, muſt needs want <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> but this I affirme; <hi>conſcience</hi> is in the reaſonable creature only, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be men or Angels, good or evill, Saints or ſinners, bleſſed Angels or collapſed Divels, this power of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is in them all.</p>
            <p>Q. In what part of man is this <hi>power</hi> ſeated?</p>
            <p>A.<note place="margin">Tota in toto &amp; tota in qualibet parte.</note> I will ſay of <hi>conſcience</hi> in the ſoule, as Philoſophers of the ſoule in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. It is in every part or faculty of the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It hath the <hi>underſtanding</hi> for its Throne and Pallace, where it is cheifly reſident, and keepeth a compleate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52020:19"/>
               <hi>Court</hi> in the whole ſoule, commonly called <hi>forum conſcientiae,</hi> and there as a Judge ſits determining and preſcribing, abſolving and condemning <hi>de jure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Its in the <hi>memory,</hi> and there it acteth as <hi>Regiſter</hi> or <hi>Recorder,</hi> readily minding and recording, witneſſing and teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>de facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Its in the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections,</hi> and there Conſcience carries it ſelfe like a <hi>Jaylour</hi> or <hi>Executioner,</hi> rendring, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, plaguing and puniſhing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one <hi>ſine respectu,</hi> without partiality.</p>
            <p>The 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> thing in the definition of <hi>conſcience</hi> is <hi>determination;</hi> Conſcience determineth what is good, what evill, what is to be done, what not to be done, and ſo excites or diſwades accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. If <hi>conſcience</hi> ſay, this muſt be done, then muſt we do it for <hi>conſcience ſake.</hi> If <hi>conſcience</hi> tells us it is evill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</note> then muſt we forbeare for <hi>conſcience ſake,</hi> i.e. out of an holy feare of God, whereby our <hi>conſcience</hi> may be preſerved pure before him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>rule</hi> by which <hi>conſcience</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth, namely, the light of Gods law;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52020:20"/>I do not ſay by the light of the word, Goſpell, or written Law, but more largely by the light of Gods law, I meane the <hi>law of Nature,</hi> written in mans heart before the word was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or Goſpell revealed. For as man had a <hi>conſcience</hi> from the beginning, ſo he had light from the beginning to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate <hi>conſcience,</hi> which was the <hi>law of Nature written in his heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The laſt thing in the deſinition of <hi>conſcience</hi> is her <hi>acting</hi> or <hi>working upon the light received;</hi> which is twofold, either <hi>acquitting,</hi> or <hi>condemning:</hi> when by her light ſhe determines what is done, that it is good or evill; ſhe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly doth <hi>excuſe</hi> or <hi>accuſe, Rom.</hi> 2.15. And thus have you <hi>conſcience</hi> in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall defined and explained.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed you what <hi>conſcience</hi> is, and in whom, namely, in the reaſonable Creature; now in ſo much as every man hath reaſon, I may ſafely conclude that every man hath <hi>conſcience:</hi> The point of Doctrine is clearly this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> There is in every man a power or faculty called <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52020:20"/>
            <p n="1">1. That there is in man a <hi>conſcience,</hi> let our Apoſtle cleare up this truth in himſelfe, how often doth he call and appeale unto <hi>conſcience</hi> upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when he was convented before the <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell,</hi> &amp; greiveous things charged upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, he appeals to <hi>conſcience. Men and Brethren, I have lived</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in all good Conſcience before God untill this day.</hi> Againe when <hi>Ananias</hi> commanded them that ſtood by to <hi>ſmite Paul</hi> on the <hi>mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.1.2.</note> and <hi>Tertullus</hi> with all his <hi>Rhetoricke</hi> before <hi>Foelix</hi> beſmeares him, calling him a <hi>peſtilent fellow,</hi> a <hi>mover of ſedition, a maintainer of the ſect of the Phariſees, a polluter of the Temple,</hi> and what not? He hath no way to caſt off all this filth, but by flying unto <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> ſhewing his enimies how far and free he was from theſe baſe aſperſions, that it was his conſtant practice to keep a <hi>Conſcience void of offence toward God and toward men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that you may not think it to be Pauls peculiar, but common to others with him, <hi>we approve our ſelves to every mans Conſcience in the ſight of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52020:21"/>
            <p>Ob. Though good men have a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> yet wicked men have not.</p>
            <p>A. It is an uſuall ſaying indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men here, when they meet with ſuch as are very hard in their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or very vitious in living, to ſay this man <hi>hath no Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you muſt underſtand their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when they ſay he hath no <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> they meane no <hi>good conſcience,</hi> or no <hi>working conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be you therefore aſſured, that there is a Conſcience in every man and woman, be they good or bad. not only in <hi>Paul,</hi> but alſo in <hi>Pilate,</hi> not only in <hi>John,</hi> but likewiſe in <hi>Judas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</note> The accurſed <hi>Jewes,</hi> wicked <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and Heatheniſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters will all acknowledge the being and working of Conſcience in them.</p>
            <p>To hold therefore that ſome men have no Conſcience, is both diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to God, and injurious to man.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A diſhonour to God, as if he had given man not a perfect, but imperfect ſoule, defective in its principall power or faculty, we confeſſe that the body of man being generated, may be mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52020:21"/>wanting a part or member,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7.</note> as an eye, an eare, a hand or foot,<note place="margin">Anima in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundendo creatur, &amp; creando in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funditur. Tho: Aqu. <hi>2.</hi> d. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>1.4.1.</hi>
               </note> becauſe it comes mediately from man: but as for the foule, being <hi>created</hi> and <hi>infuſed by God,</hi> this cannot be defective but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in all this powers and faculties, and therefore a great diſhonour to God to queſtion his workmanſhip, as men do if they deny man to have a <hi>conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anima hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeminis tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur, ſed immediatè à Deo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur.</note> which is a ſpeciall power or faculty in the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An injury to man. 1. Deny man <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> you deny him reaſon, and ſo confound him with a beaſt: but grant him a <hi>conſcience,</hi> and you grant him reaſon, and ſet him in his proper place as a Lord or maſter over beaſts.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 8.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe deny him Conſcience, you deny him a Soule, one of his Eſſentials, and ſo confound his manhood, which were a great injury to him. We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſin hath brought us to a great loſſe, but not to ſuch a loſſe as to looſe our being: we have by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin loſt our <hi>innocency,</hi> but not our <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;</hi> our <hi>Excellency,</hi> but not our <hi>exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence;</hi> our ſoule is <hi>defiled,</hi> not <hi>annìhila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52020:22"/>our powers <hi>depraved,</hi> not <hi>deſtroyed;</hi> man is man ſtill, hath body and ſoule, partes, members, powers and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, all good <hi>quoad bonum naturale;</hi> all naught <hi>quoad bonum morale.</hi> The truth then ſtill ſtands cleare, that there is in every man a <hi>power or faculty called Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reaſons why God hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this power of <hi>conſcience</hi> in man are two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. R. To ſhew his Juſtice, that he will judge righteouſly. God commands judges here on earth to <hi>execute righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16</note> to proceed <hi>ſecundum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legata &amp; probata,</hi> to do nothing but upon good evidence and witneſſe. Now ſhall <hi>not the Judge of all the world do right?</hi> God hath therefore ſet this power in man, that when God comes to judge him, he may have ſufficient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in himſelfe, his owne <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence witneſſing</hi> for him or againſt him before Gods <hi>Tribunall.</hi> For God will not condemne without a <hi>witneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. R. Is to ſhew his mercy unto man: He knowes man is very fraile, &amp; <hi>labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52020:22"/>memoriae,</hi> apt to forget his God; and to forget himſelfe. Sometimes he goes forth and forgets to pray unto God for protection and direction, ſometimes he returnes home and neglects his duty of praiſe to God for his preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therefore God hath placed in him this power of <hi>conſcience</hi> as a <hi>remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> unto him.</p>
            <p>Againe ſometimes mens Paſſions are very high, as in Jonah,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> 4.9.</note> who is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to quarrell with God, and to fall out with him, as if he had greatly wronged him; God ſaith unto him, <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou well to be angry? yea</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I do well to be angry even unto death.</hi> His words are very high, words of a paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſpirit, blinded with <hi>anger,</hi> rather then with any expreſſe <hi>rebellion.</hi> Very needfull therefore is it that ſuch ſhould have <hi>conſcience</hi> as a <hi>Controuler</hi> to check them.</p>
            <p>Againe, others their <hi>Affections</hi> are diſorderly placed on wrong <hi>objects,</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe whom they ſhould diſlike, and loving thoſe whom they ſhould loath; ſuch was the blind Affection of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52020:23"/>
               <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> to <hi>Ahab, I am</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as thou art,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18 3. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2.</note> 
               <hi>my people as thy people:</hi> its needfull therefore that <hi>conſcience</hi> ſay to ſuch as <hi>Jehn</hi> to <hi>Iehoſhaphat, ſhouldſt then love them that hate the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly many mens <hi>appetites</hi> are very wanton, wholſome meates and drinkes content them not, their meates muſt be mixed with hurtfull condiments, and their drinke with noxious ingredients, therefore it is very requiſite that <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> play the Monitor, and adviſe them <hi>not to looke on the wine when it ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>nor to ſeeke after mixt wine: though it goe downe pleaſantly,</hi> yet at laſt it will <hi>bite like a Serpent, and hurt like a Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice.</hi> And thus you ſee how juſt and how mercifull God is, to plant ſuch a power as <hi>conſcience</hi> within us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Is there ſuch a power or faculty as <hi>conſcience</hi> in every man, then let every man learne to magnify his maker, not barely for being his Creature, but for being ſuch a Creature as none is like him.</p>
            <p>Firſt look upon thy meaneſt part, namely, thy body, view that well, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52020:23"/>thou ſhalt ſee ſuch an exellency in it, that no viſible creature is comparable unto mans body. If we look unto our firſt Creation, we find them very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent creatures.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God made them with conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deliberation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>(let us make man.)</hi> His advice argueth a worke of great weight and moment, and this word of plurality <hi>(us)</hi> intimates the Trinity,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Galen though a meere Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſt, when he ſaw the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable frame and ſtructure of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, was ſo taken with it that he could not but adiudge the honour of an Hymne to the wiſe Creator of it.</note> and mindes us of the myſterie of the three perſons in one Godhead. God the father ſeemeth to ſpeak, as commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating by way of conſultation with God the Son, and God the holy Ghoſt in the worke of Creation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The wonderfull endowments of the body in beauty, ſtrength, nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, activity, without deformity or mortality.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All other bodies made for the good of mans body, the heavenly to give light unto it, the earthly bodies to nouriſh, cheriſh, and comfort it.</p>
            <p>Againe, if we conſider the <hi>recreation</hi> or <hi>regeneration</hi> of our bodies, we find them more excellent.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52020:24"/>
            <p n="1">1. Purchaſed by Chriſts bloud, 1 Cor. 6.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sanctified by Chriſts ſpirit, 1 Cor. 6.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Aſſumed by Chriſts perſon, Phil. 2.7. When he took our nature, he took our body, and <hi>was made like unto us in all things, ſin only excepted,</hi> ſo that we are as neer to Chriſt, as our bodies to our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Having thus viewed our meaneſt part, namely, the body; let us in the next place conſider our beſt part, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our ſoule.</p>
            <p>What the ſoule is: The ſoule of man is a ſpirit diſtinct, inviſible, immortall, infuſed by God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A ſpirit. Thus much the Originall word declareth, as in John 11. 33. and John 12. 27. we find ſoule and ſpirit promiſcuouſly uſed by our Saviour, <hi>my ſoule is troubled, my spirit is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A diſtinct ſpirit, becauſe it hath its being not only in the body, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo out of the body,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7.</note> as it had its time of entrance into the body, ſo its time
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52020:24"/>of <hi>returne</hi> out. As it is in us, ſo it can be without us, and will be after us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Inviſible. Becauſe no more to be ſeen then an Angel or God himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. An immortall ſpirit. Eccl. 12.7. And Chriſt tells us, that men may <hi>kill our bodies,</hi> but not <hi>our ſoules,</hi> which made <hi>Anaxzarchus</hi> bold to ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Tormentors, who did beat him with clubs, laye on my Sachel, meaning his <hi>body,</hi> you cannot hurt <hi>Anaxzar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> meaning his <hi>ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A ſpirit infuſed by God, Gen. 2.7. How Adam came by his ſoule we all know, namely, by inſpiration, but as for our owne ſoules we are at a great ſtand. Some think by participation,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Chryſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur â. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as one Candle lighteth another. Some thinke by generation,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian l. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim â ch <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that a man begets a man compleat. Others ſay it is by infuſion,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Thom. Aquin. <hi>1</hi> q. <hi>75.6. 1</hi> m.</note> by a peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, when the child is firſt quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened in the womb. Much is imagined little concluded concerning this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,<note n="(e)" place="margin">St. Auſtin hath writ <hi>4</hi> bookes of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the ſoule, in which he leaveth this queſtion undecided. And his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke of Retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions doth witneſſe that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in that doubt unto his death. cap. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> and no marvell, for who knoweth the way of the ſpirit, Eccl. 11.5.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52020:25"/>
            <p>The Scripture ſeems to warrant the laſt opinion, calling God the Creator of the Spirit, Zach. 12.1. The giver of the Spirit, Eccl. 12.7. The Father of our ſpirits, Heb. 12.9. It is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration, if God by a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar elegy and ſtile, is called the <hi>father of ſpirits,</hi> that he might be oppoſed to the <hi>father of the fleſh;</hi> for if the ſoule be by traduction, then thoſe that are the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the fleſh</hi> would alſo be the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſpirits:</hi> neither would God by this title be diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>father of the fleſh,</hi> if he wrought alike in both, and did not forme mens ſoules otherwiſe then their bodies. So then conſider well your bodies &amp; ſoules, and you may ſafely conclude that of all the creatures that ever God made, there is more to be ſeen of God in man then in them all, and in man, much in his <hi>body,</hi> more in his <hi>ſoule,</hi> but moſt of all in his <hi>conſcience,</hi> (as one ſaith) this ſmelleth more of God, then the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the Sun, the Stars, or all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things of the earth, gold, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, Rubies, or ſweeteſt herbs,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52020:25"/>roſes, or lillies. Oh how ſhould we magnifie our maker,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.14.</note> and with David ſay, <hi>I will praiſe thee O Lord, for I am fearfully and wonderfully made; marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous are thy workes and that my ſoule knoweth right well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object: </seg>
               </label> Ob. Our <hi>conſcience</hi> were at firſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pure and excellent, but now like our ſelves they are moſt ſinfull, yea our <hi>Soules and Conſciences are defiled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing worthy praiſe in them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw: </seg>
               </label> A. Its very true that our <hi>conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> which were pure and excellent at firſt, are by <hi>Adam's</hi> ſin become defiled and uncleane. But let me tell you there is no part, power or faculty in the whole man, that retaines ſo much of its excellency in it as <hi>conſcience</hi> doth, though the whole ſoule were defiled, and every part and power depraved, yet <hi>conſcience</hi> had ſo much life left in it, as (with <hi>Iobs meſſengers</hi>) to tell ſad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of mans great loſſe. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in it <hi>ſcintilla rectae rationis,</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpark to ſhew what great light hath been extinguiſht, but now this alſo through affected blindneſſe and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52020:26"/>malice is ſo ſmothered and ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through a daiely cuſtome of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that I may ſay of <hi>conſcience</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as the Pſalmiſt of an Idol, <hi>it hath an eye and cannot ſee, an eare and cannot heare, a mouth and cannot ſpeak.</hi> Thus ſtands the cauſe whith many a hardned ſinner. The eye of their <hi>conſcience</hi> is as the eye of a <hi>mole,</hi> which ſerves only to decore the body, but not to guide the way. Their eares but as the eares of an <hi>Addar,</hi> wilfully ſtopt at the beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell that the meſſenger of Chriſt can bring unto it, and the mouth of it as the mouth of a <hi>viper,</hi> that ſucks in and ſends out nothing but poiſon and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous expreſſions. Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>naturall Conſcience</hi> will hold an excellency beyond all other powers &amp; faculties in the ſoule. So that thy Maker ſtill deſerveth praiſe from thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>2</label> Have all a <hi>conſcience,</hi> then let all acknowledge it and not dare to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale what God hath given them. Its very dangerous to <hi>hide any Talent</hi> that God gives us <hi>in a Napkin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> what God beſtowes on man, man is to imploy and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52020:26"/>uſe it to the honour of him that gives it: therefore let <hi>conſcience</hi> appeare in a conſcientious walking before him, be holy to thy God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12.</note> upright to thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſober in thy ſelfe, walke ſo circumſpectly in thy place and calling, that all may ſay thou art a man of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> But woe unto us we <hi>ſojourne in Meſech, our habitations are in Kedar,</hi> we live among ſuch as are enimies to <hi>conſcience,</hi> yea open and profeſſed eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies unto it: yea the very naming of <hi>conſcience</hi> is very hatefull unto them, aske them where their <hi>conſcience</hi> is, and they will deſperately anſwer, what tell you me of <hi>conſcience? Conſcience</hi> (ſay they) was hanged long ago. But let me tell thee thou wretched <hi>Belialiſt,</hi> that ſaieſt that <hi>conſcience</hi> is hang'd, waſt thou the Hangman? If ſo; then know God will be avenged on thee for this cruell act, he will one day revive <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and then aſſure thy ſelfe thy <hi>conſcience</hi> will hang thee.</p>
            <p>But hear me (thou fooliſh man) that thus talkeſt of hanging <hi>conſcience,</hi> thou ſpeakeſt not only prophanely but moſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52020:27"/>ignorantly thinkeſt thou it is in the power of any man to hang <hi>conſcience,</hi> know thou, it is impoſſible, the worke is too hard for all the hangmen in the world. The Hangman may hang thee as he did <hi>Haman,</hi> or thou mayeſt hang thy ſelfe as did <hi>Judas,</hi> but neither he nor thou art able to offer ſuch violence to <hi>conſcience.</hi> Wer'ſt thou to live as long as <hi>Methuſalem,</hi> it will outlive thee; go where thou wilt, it will go with thee, <hi>nec fugere nec fugare poteris,</hi> go up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> or go downe to <hi>Hell,</hi> 'twill never leave thee nor forſake thee.</p>
            <p>Againe I find ſome who are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly bent againſt <hi>conſcience,</hi> that they reſolve, if they cannot hang <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> they will beat out her teeth, and pluck out her tongue, ſo that ſhe ſhall neither bite nor barke, if the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, the pride of life, if all the pleaſures of ſin will do it, they will ſurely effect it. They will call for the harp with <hi>Saul,</hi> for their Cup with <hi>Nabal,</hi> and their Harlot with <hi>Herod,</hi> and all to drowne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52020:27"/>the cryes and complaints of <hi>conſcience:</hi> but let me tell ſuch, that thus labour to make <hi>conſcience</hi> dumb, poſſible it is that by a long cuſtome in ſin, or greedy practice of it, men may prevaile ſo far, as to ſilence her for the preſent, ſo that ſhe ſhall not ſpeak: but know this, though you keep <hi>conſcience</hi> from ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, yet not from writing, ſhe will act the part of a Recorder and Regiſter, put downe exactly every daies deviati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and aberrations, and when ſhee ſees her time, will produce her Bill and read it aloud, making thine eares to tingle, now a lie, and then an oath, this time drunkenneſſe, that time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe, ſuch a day thou tookeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy Brothers goods, by oppreſſion and theevery; another day his good name, by ſlaunder and calumny. In fine the Bill will be ſo <hi>bigg,</hi> ſo <hi>black,</hi> that thou wilt not be able to endure to heare it read. And then thy <hi>conſcience</hi> whom thou haſt thus wronged, will be avenged for all her wrongs, and act the part of a <hi>Judge,</hi> a <hi>Jaylour,</hi> and a <hi>Tormentour,</hi> and joine with her God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52020:28"/>in that black and moſt juſt ſentence, <hi>take him, bind him hand and foot, and caſt him into utter darkneſſe, where there ſhall be nothing but weeping, wailing, gnaſhing of teeth, and that for ever.</hi> Oh <hi>conſider this</hi> ye that abuſe Conſcience, <hi>leſt ſhe teare you in pieces, when none ſhall deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Uſe of Conviction unto all <hi>Athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall</hi> perſons that dare ſay with their tongue, or in <hi>their heart, there is no God.</hi> Tell me thou Atheiſt, haſt thou a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> in thee, and yet no God over thee? how can this be? if thou wilt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy ſelfe to be lead by common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thou then wilt be forced to ſay there is a God. Conſider the operation of thy <hi>conſcience,</hi> if it be not ſeared; and thou ſhalt find that upon ſome groſſe ſin, it will be a witneſſe and give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt thee, but to whom? to men or Angels? that cannot be, for they cannot heare the voice of <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> nor receive <hi>conſciences</hi> teſtimony, neither can they ſee what is in the heart of man, It remains therefore that there is a ſpirituall ſubſtance, moſt wiſe, moſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52020:28"/>holy, moſt mighty, that ſees &amp; knows all things, to whom <hi>conſcience</hi> beares record, and that is God himſelfe. Let <hi>Atheiſts</hi> bark againſt this as long as they will: they have that in them that will convince them of the truth of the Godhead (will they, nill they) either in life or death. Let the dreaming A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt conſider the great affliction that that ſevere Governeſſe of the life of man brings upon their ſoules by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting <hi>horrors of Conſcience,</hi> by puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeling and befooling them in the free uſe of their <hi>Reaſon;</hi> by curbing them in their naturall and kindly injoyments in the life preſent, and making bitter all the pleaſures and contentment of it by ſome checks of Conſcience: by anxious <hi>cares</hi> and diſquieting <hi>feares</hi> concerning their ſtate in the life to come. Beſides thoſe ineffable agonies of mind, dampes and deadneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that they ſometimes undergoe, ſo that to be buried quick were leſſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by far, then ſuch dark heart-ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king privations of all the joyes of life. And they cannot chuſe (did they not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52020:29"/>ſhut their eyes againſt the light) but ſee that there is a <hi>ſuperintendent princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> over nature, which is all one as to confeſſe that <hi>there is a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thou be not convinced by the working of thine owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> then conſider the workings of <hi>conſcience</hi> in others: what makes <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>run into the thicket, sarah</hi> to <hi>ſtand behind the Tent door, Jonah to lurke downe in the ſide of the ſhip, Cain</hi> to feare a mortall blow from <hi>every man he meets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 20 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22 25.</note> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> to be a terror unto themſelves, and to run <hi>from chamber to chamber to hide</hi> themſelves. It was their <hi>conſcience,</hi> and nothing but <hi>conſcience</hi> accuſing and teſtifying unto God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>Againe conſider, how is it, that when God is pleaſed to give out unto us a notable ſigne of is power and maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as in thunder and lightning, that the very ſound of the one, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſight of the other (though theſe be but from Naturall cauſes) ſhould make a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> a contemner of God, to ſhake and tremble. Againe whence is it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52020:29"/>that there is a Religions Adoration and propenſion to the worſhip of a Deity even in thoſe Heathens themſelves, who ſacrifice <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God.</hi> There being no nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven, that does not do divine worſhip to ſome thing or other, and in it to God as they conceive. So that they worſhip many of them but ſtocks and ſtones, and ſome particular piece of nature, as the Sun, Moone, or Stars, knowing that there is ſomewhat to whom worſhip belongs. Therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ordinary <hi>naturall light</hi> that is in all men, there is a God. Oh therefore bluſh and bewaile thy damnable <hi>Atheiſme.</hi> Conſider well theſe things, know and underſtand, ſee and ſay, <hi>verily there is a God that judgeth the earth.</hi> thus far of <hi>conſcience</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken of the faculty, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>conſcience,</hi> we now proceed unto the Qualitie, namely, a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> Had <hi>Paul</hi> onely ſaid, I have, or I am aſſured I have a <hi>conſcience,</hi> he had ſaid no more then a Reprobate or Devill might have ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52020:30"/>
            <p>But in that he ſaith, he hath a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> and that he is fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the ſame, in this he goes beyond all reprobates and Devils, who neither have, nor ever ſhall have ſuch a boſome friend within them.</p>
            <p>We muſt now diſtinguiſh <hi>conſcience</hi> into two <hi>ſpecies,</hi> namely, good and evill.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Honeſtè bona, paca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè bona.</note> A good Conſcience, 1 Tim. 1.19. <hi>Holding faith and a good Conſcience.</hi> This good Conſcience is ſometimes quiet, ſometimes unquiet.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Vitiosè mala, mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtè mala. Bern: Ames.</note> An evill Conſcience Heb. 10.22. <hi>having our hearts ſprinkled from an evill Conſcience.</hi> This is likewiſe peaceable or turbulent. Now how theſe two do differ both in their peace and their trouble, I ſhall hereafter ſhew you.</p>
            <p>I am now to ſpeak of the firſt, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>a good conſcience,</hi> and more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Pauls good Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What a <hi>good conſcience</hi> is? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>good conſcience</hi> is a Conſcience rightly informed and principled by the word, ſo that it can truly judge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52020:30"/>evill to be evill, and good to be good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By a <hi>good conſcience</hi> I underſtand a <hi>conſcience</hi> ſanctified by the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, whereby we are incited to good, and diſwaded from evill, and doth readily <hi>excuſe</hi> us for doing well, but <hi>accuſe</hi> us for doing evill.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By <hi>Pauls good conſcience</hi> in the Text, I underſtand a <hi>conſcience</hi> both <hi>purified and pacifyed by the blood and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt,</hi> ſo that upon a true ſight and ſorrow for ſin, and a full perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the remiſſion of the ſame in and for Chriſt, he enjoyed that <hi>peace which paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 4.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</note> (i. e.) a true ſpirituall and incomprehenſible reſt and quietneſſe of mind, wrought by Gods ſpirit in his heart, and ſo preſerving him from terror, anxiety, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>But to draw unto ſome profitable point of Doctrine, you heare <hi>Paul</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in a <hi>good conſcience;</hi> not as his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar, as if he only were the man thus bleſſed of God, but doth acknowledge the like mercy to be ſhewed by God
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52020:31"/>unto others, and therefore mentioning thoſe that laboured with him in the Goſpell, ſpeaketh in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>(we) are aſſured we have a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> So that we may ſafely conlude that as all men have a <hi>conſcience,</hi> ſo there are ſome that have a <hi>good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some there are, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> who have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Conſcience, but alſo a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>Of this ſome, I find <hi>Noah a juſt man and perfect in his generation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>and one that walked with God</hi> (i. e.) ſincerely in his profeſſion of Religion without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy. <hi>Moſes</hi> the meekeſt on the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3.</note> one that deſpiſed the vaine and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing honour, riches, pleaſures of the world, <hi>chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon. Job</hi> a <hi>none<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuch,</hi> none like him on the <hi>earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſo <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> ſo <hi>upright,</hi> that <hi>feared God and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed evill; David a man after Gods owne heart; Nathaniel, a true Iſraelite indeed, in whom is no guile</hi> (i. e.) a man of ſimple integrity.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> John.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> a continuall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52020:31"/>practitioner of a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it his daiely practice to <hi>keep a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence both towards God &amp; towards man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16.</note> Thus might I tire you out with a long Catalogue of bleſſed Saints, who lived in <hi>all good conſcience</hi> from their <hi>converſion</hi> unto their <hi>diſſolution.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. How came theſe to have a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> ſeeing all by nature have their <hi>conſciences defiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 1. They had the <hi>bloud of Chriſt</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied unto their <hi>conſciences,</hi> whereby they were <hi>purged</hi> from the impurity of <hi>dead workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note> it being the <hi>fountaine for ſin and for uncleanneſſe,</hi> (<hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1.) in which poor loathſome, leperous ſoules waſh and are cleanſed: they were put into this poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> and came out cleane, being made white in the blood of the Lamb.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They had the <hi>righteouſneſſe of Chriſt</hi> imputed unto them, whereby they were diſcharged from the debt of ſin, all <hi>hand-writings</hi> of accuſations being cancel'd, and they eſteemed holy and unblameable in the ſight of God, Rom. 5.1. Not for any thing wrought
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52020:32"/>in them and done by them, but for Chriſts ſake alone. Not by imputing faith it ſelfe, or any other Evangelicall obedience, but by imputing the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſatisfaction of Chriſt as their righteouſneſſe, received and reſted on by faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They by diligence in Chriſtian watchfulneſſe do maintaine their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, and if caſually by any ſlip they ſeemed to break the peace, they were carefull to renue their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by true humiliation and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, earneſtly doing their firſt works and redeeming their former <hi>negligence</hi> with double <hi>diligence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Q. Whether a man may not have a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> yet the ſame to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>unquiet</hi> and much troubled?</p>
            <p>Anſw: You muſt know that there is a 4 fold <hi>conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Good and quiet. <hi>Purifyed</hi> and <hi>pacifyed,</hi> which reſts in a ſweet feeling of the mercies of God in Chriſt. Such a <hi>conſcience</hi> had <hi>Paul that teſtifyed unto him, that in ſimplicity and Godly ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he had his converſation.</hi> And <hi>Hezekiah</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52020:32"/>when he was upon his death bed (as he thought) his <hi>conſcience</hi> gave him a <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall</hi> that commended him to God better then all the men in the world could, that he <hi>walked before the Lord in truth and in a perfect heart, and did that which was right in his ſight.</hi> Iſ. 38.3 This ſweet peace of a good Conſcience flowes from a certaine inexpreſſible aſſurance, that we are the <hi>ſons of God,</hi> a certaine ſecret manifeſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God hath receiv'd us &amp; put away our ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither good nor quiet. When the heart is as full of ſin, as hell of darkneſſe, and lies under a ſerious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Gods wrath, and a <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine looking for of vengeance and fiery indignation to devoure,</hi> Heb. 10.27. and is in a forlorn condition, not knowing where to go for help, but God is to him as the <hi>burning fire</hi> to the <hi>withered ſtubble,</hi> and as the <hi>ſcorching flame</hi> to the <hi>melted wax.</hi> Thus the cauſe ſtood with <hi>Judas,</hi> who after he had committed that curſed fact of <hi>betraying</hi> his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> he was ſo gnawed by the worme <hi>conſcience,</hi> that nothing but an halter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52020:33"/>could eaſe him; <hi>he hang'd himſelfe.</hi> And certainly had not Hell gaped for him, he had got by the bargaine. This made <hi>Cain</hi> go in continuall feare of <hi>killing,</hi> and the <hi>perſecuting Tyrant</hi> to caſt up his bowels towards heaven and ſay, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti Galilaee, thou haſt overcome O Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Quiet but not good. This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the beſt of men, and they bleſſe themſelves in it, that they never had a bad word from <hi>conſcience</hi> all their daies, it doth not trouble nor terrify them; certainly ſuch a Conſcience is <hi>ſeared with an hot iron,</hi> and who ever is thus <hi>ſtigmatiz'd,</hi> is marked for a Rebbell againſt God. They ſleep in their ſins like <hi>Jonah in the ſtorme,</hi> though they are in greateſt danger to be caſt into the gulfe and ſea of Gods everlaſting wrath.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Good but not quiet. And ſuch doubtleſſe a child of God may have; Examples are many, as in <hi>Job</hi> chap. 6. 4. <hi>The Arrowes of the Lord are within me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>the poiſon whereof drinketh up my spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: the terrors of the Lord do ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in array againſt me.</hi> So David,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52020:33"/>
               <hi>thine arrowes ſtick faſt in me, and thy hand preſſeth me ſore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>there is no ſoundneſſe in my fleſh, becauſe of thine anger: neither any reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia bona &amp; turbata. Bern:</note> 
               <hi>For mine iniquities are gone over mine head, as an heavy burden they are too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy for me.</hi> Thus <hi>Ezekiah</hi> and others. But at ſuch times though they have a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> yet do they faile in <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 38.2, 3, 4.</note> they have <hi>Paul's conſcience,</hi> but not <hi>Pauls confidence,</hi> it is the latter, not the former that makes it quiet and inoffenſive: and ſuch was Pauls conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not only good, but quiet and inoffenſive. Chriſtians have ſomtimes <hi>Cleare Sunſhini dayes,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>darke cloudy daies,</hi> ſometimes they are under a cloud, and the light of Gods countenance doth not ſhine on them; ſometimes they <hi>behold the face of God in righteouſneſſe,</hi> and his <hi>favour is better to them then life.</hi> Sometimes (like <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi>) they are in the <hi>bitterneſſe of their ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtè bona, &amp; pacatè bona <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> and drinke of the bitter <hi>waters of Marah,</hi> which makes them <hi>go mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all their daies;</hi> ſo then it may ſtand with a child of God to have a diſquiet,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52020:34"/>troubled Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Uſe for Tryall, whether we be of that <hi>ſome</hi> that <hi>have a good Conſcience,</hi> he that will not try, <hi>wants it;</hi> he that tries ſuperficially, hath cauſe to <hi>doubt it;</hi> but he that is exact and ſincere may ſafely <hi>conclude,</hi> I am aſſured <hi>I have a good Conſcience:</hi> therefore ſearch your ſelves as with Candles and Torches, whether you can find this precious <hi>Jewell of a good conſcience</hi> treaſurd up within you, yea or no. And the better to incite you to a true and diligent <hi>Triall,</hi> take theſe 2 Motives.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The neer reſemblance between a <hi>Naturall</hi> and <hi>Spirituall</hi> Conſcience,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">
                  <hi>Motives</hi> to a diligent Triall.</note> and that in divers reſpects. They both have their conflicts, both their loathing of ſin, they both ſeeme to turne <hi>a broad-ſide</hi> againſt ſin, and to complaine againſt it. The <hi>Naturall conſcience</hi> ſaith I ſee the better, but I follow the worſe; The <hi>Spirituall conſcience</hi> ſaith, <hi>the good which I would do, I do not, but the evill which I would not do, that do I.</hi> See here the difference, in the <hi>latter,</hi> there is a will ſtriving againſt ſin: but in the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:52020:34"/>no will, no ſtriving at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Naturall conſcience</hi> is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled only by ſome generall grounds of <hi>Nature,</hi> acting and making <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> ſo far as his rules and <hi>principles</hi> will carry him, and ſo deceiveth the Naturall man, making him to boaſt of what he hath not, namely a <hi>good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Whereas the ſpirituall Conſcience rightly principled by <hi>Gods word,</hi> and ſanctified <hi>by his Spirit</hi> makes the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to have a <hi>good Conſcience in all things,</hi> Heb. 13.18. making <hi>conſcience</hi> of all that God commands or forbids, Pſ. 119.6.101. Be therefore carefull in <hi>trying</hi> your ſelves, 2 Cor. 13.5. And that you may not be deceived take theſe 5 markes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He that hath a good <hi>conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Notes of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> can truly ſay, that what he doth, <hi>he doth it for Conſcience ſake;</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſtirrs him up unto the duty, and he cannot ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <hi>conſcience,</hi> if he neglect it: He ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects himſelfe to God, and he ſubjects himſelfe to man, and this not for wrath but <hi>conſcience.</hi> See well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this, and the rather,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</note> becauſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52020:35"/>Many there are, whoſe <hi>Actions</hi> are very ſpecious, and yet without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>conſcience. Salomon</hi> deſcribing a good man, ſaith, he is <hi>one that feareth an oath;</hi> he doth not ſay that he is one that ſweareth not, but one that <hi>feareth an oath:</hi> poſſible it is that a man may not ſweare and why, becauſe he hath been well <hi>educated,</hi> or he ſtandeth in awe of his <hi>Parents</hi> or Governours, or feareth ſome mulct from the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate;</hi> this is no teſtimony of a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> But if a man ſweare not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he feareth an Oath;</hi> this argueth that the man feareth the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to feare the commandement is a ſure note of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.13.</note> The leaſt haire makes the eye weep, ſo the leaſt ſin makes the heart ſmite. Now as in avoiding of <hi>ſin,</hi> ſo in practiſing <hi>piety,</hi> a man reads the Scripture at home, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the word preached in publick, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes duties in his <hi>family.</hi> But why doth he thus? if to ſatisfy <hi>conſcience</hi> in obedience unto God tis well; but if baſe and ſiniſter ends to pleaſe and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy his owne carnall deſire, this is baſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52020:35"/>and far from a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi> We find the <hi>Shechemites</hi> groſſe hypocrites in this, they will joine with <hi>Gods people,</hi> and doe as they doe; be <hi>circumciſed</hi> as they are; had this been done out of <hi>conſcience,</hi> it would have rejoyced the hearts of all godly ones; but here is no ſuch thing, they will be circumciſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not to pleaſe God, but to pleaſe <hi>Hamor</hi> and <hi>Shechem</hi> their Rulers, and to enrich themſelves, <hi>(ſhall not their goods and their cattell be ours?)</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 34.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus many now adaies amongſt us will make ſome ſhew of religion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme holy duties both <hi>publikely</hi> and <hi>privately,</hi> not out of <hi>conſcience</hi> but out of <hi>carnall policy.</hi> They have learned <hi>Matchiavels maxime, to ſeem religious is a credit, but to be neligious is a cumber.</hi> Its only a <hi>forme</hi> without <hi>power,</hi> a <hi>ſhew</hi> without <hi>ſubſtance.</hi> They ſet not <hi>God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes,</hi> neither do they with Moſes <hi>ſee him that is inviſible:</hi> they look only unto men, and all their ayme is how they may <hi>pleaſe</hi> men, and <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> themſelves in earthly things. Therefore if you will be ſure your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52020:36"/>is good, do what you do, for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> not becauſe man thinks it fit, and you think it <hi>profitable</hi> or <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,</hi> but becauſe God commands it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Note. If you have a <hi>good conſcience</hi> then will you ſuffer what you ſuffer, <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> yea to ſatisfy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. This is <hi>praiſe worthy</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19.</note> 1 Pet. 2.19. when a man for <hi>conſcience</hi> towards God endures greife, ſuffers wrong, and as his <hi>precept,</hi> ſo his <hi>practice;</hi> had rather be puniſhed for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, then praiſed for doing evill. See this in <hi>Daniel,</hi> he will ſuffer hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, feed upon Pulſe, rather then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file his <hi>conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.8.</note> The three <hi>Children</hi> will chuſe rather to have their bodies burned in <hi>ſchorching flames,</hi> then to have them bowed to a <hi>baſe Idol.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> had rather that <hi>Ananias</hi> ſhould ſmite him, then that his <hi>conſcience</hi> ſhould ſmite him.</p>
            <p>Try thy ſelfe therefore by this Note, doeſt thou ſuffer, and doeſt thou ſo ſuffer as to <hi>ſatisfy conſcience,</hi> patiently bearing it, becauſe God will have it ſo,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52020:36"/>as <hi>David</hi> in the railing of <hi>Shimei,</hi> he <hi>curſeth me, becauſe God hath ſaid unto him, curſe David.</hi> Not that God ſaid ſo much by word, but by a command of providence, ſo ordering and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Shimei</hi> his malice, as to make it a <hi>rod</hi> to correct and chaſtiſe <hi>David</hi> for his ſin;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.20.</note> but as a <hi>Scorpion</hi> to <hi>Shimei</hi> to ſting him to death and deſtruction. Thus did <hi>Job</hi> in all his troubles, beare with them with wonderfull <hi>patience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 1.21.</note> he will not <hi>charge God fooliſhly,</hi> but ſaith <hi>the Lord giveth, the Lord taketh away, praiſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas how many now amongſt us would be accounted men of a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> and yet will ſuffer nothing for <hi>conſcience.</hi> They will ſuffer no greife, no paine, no loſſe for it. See this in <hi>Amaziah</hi> King of Judah, he hires an Army of an 100000 men of valour out of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 25.6.</note> for an hundred Talents of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but God diſlikes his hired men, and ſends a <hi>Prophet</hi> unto <hi>Amaziah</hi> to diſmiſſe them. The King tells the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>what ſhall I do for the</hi> 100 <hi>Talents?</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, I have diſbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52020:37"/>a great ſumme of monyes, &amp; ſhall I now looſe all? You may ſee how loath he is to looſe his money, 100 Talents of ſilver a great ſumme. But alas what is 100 Talents to a good <hi>conſcience?</hi> yet look abroad in the world, and you may then deſcend from Talents to pounds, from pounds to pence, and from pence to farthings, and find ſome yea a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, that if a farthing and a <hi>good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> ſtand in competition, they will looſe their Conſcience to ſave their farthing.</p>
            <p>Heare this you Tradeſmen, Typlers, Retailers, and all that have any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce in buying, and ſelling, witneſſe this truth with me; how often have you, and that upon the Lords day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred your <hi>owne houſes</hi> before <hi>Gods houſe?</hi> your t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pling gueſts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Cuſtomers before Gods mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and ſervants? chuſing rather to gaine a <hi>Triſle at home,</hi> then to gaine <hi>ſalvation abroad</hi> in attending on Gods holy ordinances. Yea let me ſay yet more unto you, how often hath your <hi>conſcience</hi> blamed you for ſo doing, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52020:37"/>you, whereas you ſhould have hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto <hi>conſcience</hi> voice, have <hi>ſtopt your eares</hi> and blamed <hi>conſcience</hi> for too much ſtrictneſſe, too much tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; what mean theſe words of yours? If I ſhould be ſo ſtrict in my dealings as Preachers would have me to be, I might ſoon pluck down my ſigne, ſhut up my ſhop, &amp; ſit ſtill and do nothing. Let me tell ſuch, theſe words ſavour not of a <hi>good,</hi> but an <hi>evill Conſcience.</hi> God puts none of his into ſuch ſtreights, as that they cannot live except they live unholily, unjuſtly. Believe it, as there is no calling, be it never ſo high, that muſt call thee from God, ſo there is no calling be it never ſo low, that muſt give thee a diſpenſation to diſhonour God. And as in the greateſt calling men may live both fully and faithfully; ſo in the meaneſt calling, if men uſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with conſcience, they may live <hi>honeſtly</hi> and yet <hi>comfortably.</hi> Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Beloved caſt off ſuch gaine, as filthy lucre; ſuch cuſtomers, as your great enimies: and take up this holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution never to make haſt for wealth,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52020:38"/>nor to uſe any unlawfull meanes for this tranſitory Traſh, but ſay, if I begg I begg, if I ſtarve I ſtarve, I will looſe all, rather then looſe a <hi>good conſcience</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Note of a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> is bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for God and in Gods cauſe. <hi>The righteous are as bold as a Lyon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.1</note> Prov. 28.1. When the <hi>conſcience</hi> is good, the <hi>courage</hi> is great, it will make a man to have a Lions heart and an Angels face; ſuch an heart had <hi>Paul,</hi> when he looked on the Councell, Act. 23.1. ſuch a face had <hi>Stephen</hi> the Proto-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.21 &amp; 15.6.</note> Act. 6.15. All that ſate in the <hi>Councell looking ſtedfaſtly on him, ſaw his face as if it had been the face of an Angel.</hi> This <hi>good conſcience</hi> will make a mans <hi>face as a flint</hi> againſt ſuch as <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez.</hi> 3.8, 9.</note> Ezek. 3.8, 9.</p>
            <p>Let but God call upon ſuch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ:</hi> 41.10, 13.14.</note> ſaying, <hi>feare not worme Jacob, for I am with thee, be not afraid, for I am thy God:</hi> or let him ſtand by them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.11</note> as he did by <hi>Paul,</hi> and bid him <hi>be of good cheer:</hi> They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently take ſuch courage unto them, that having God for them, they feare not who are <hi>againſt them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 3.6.</note> David will
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52020:38"/>not feare an <hi>hoaſt of men, Athanaſius</hi> a <hi>world of men,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Fox in the ſtory of Martin Luther. p. <hi>849.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> will not feare a <hi>multitude of Divels,</hi> were they in number as many, as there were Tiles upon the houſes of <hi>Wormes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas where are theſe valiant ones become? we have many very <hi>couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> for themſelves, and in what makes for their owne intereſt: but as for God and in his cauſe they are very <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are <hi>bold for ſin,</hi> but <hi>baſhfull for ſanctity;</hi> they can plead for <hi>Baal,</hi> but <hi>not for God:</hi> And yet ſuch would be accounted men of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let me tell ſuch they do much deceive themſelves, as they have not <hi>Pauls courage,</hi> ſo neither <hi>Pauls conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and as they are ſtrangers to a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> ſo are they ſtrangers to a moſt <hi>good God,</hi> who will be ſo far from <hi>bleſſing them,</hi> that he will ſurely <hi>curſe them,</hi> and give ſuch timerous and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſons, which want the fire of zeale, their part in the <hi>lake that burneth with fire and brimeſtone, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.</hi> Rev. 21.8.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:52020:39"/>
            <p>A Childlike heart can never be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent under Gods <hi>diſhonour,</hi> though he is alwaies ſilent under his <hi>displeaſure. Moſes</hi> was <hi>coole in his owne cauſe,</hi> but <hi>hot when Gods credit</hi> lay at ſtake. When the <hi>children of Iſrael</hi> had wrought <hi>folly in the golden Calfe,</hi> the <hi>zeale of God did ſo eat him up,</hi> that he could as well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fire <hi>in his boſome,</hi> as be patient, when Gods glory ſuffer'd.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore try your ſelves upon this Note, and before you find your ſelves more <hi>bold for God,</hi> be not ſo bold as to boaſt of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Note of a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> is to love a Conſcientious <hi>Teacher</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer: he deſires not to live under a cold, man-pleaſing miniſtry, which preaches liberty, not ſtrictneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which <hi>ſoweth pillowes under mens armeholes, and cryeth peace, peace,</hi> ſo that <hi>none departeth from his evill way.</hi> The <hi>good conſcience</hi> deſireth ſuch a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, who is not ſhaken with <hi>feare,</hi> nor ſeduced with <hi>flattery,</hi> whoſe voice is the voice of a <hi>cryer;</hi> his ſound as the ſound of a <hi>trumpet;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſai</hi> 58.1.</note> his words like
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52020:39"/>
               <hi>ſharp nailes</hi> and <hi>piercing goads;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> his <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> an <hi>heart-pricking;</hi> his dividing of his Text and matter the <hi>dividing aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſoule and ſpirit, of the joints and marrow.</hi> Such we find amongſt the Prophets, that <hi>cryed aloud and did not ſpare to tell the people of their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the houſe of Judah of their ſins.</hi> Such were amongſt the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were <hi>ſons of Thunder,</hi> and threatned judgments againſt the wicked and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious:</hi> Yea Chriſt himſelfe, who had the <hi>tongue of the learned to ſpeake the word in ſeaſon to him that was weary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.4.</note> was alſo as a <hi>poliſhed ſhaft,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.2.</note> and his mouth as a <hi>ſharp ſword,</hi> his eyes as a <hi>flame of fire,</hi> and his <hi>comming</hi> into the <hi>Temple</hi> none was able to abide: he was as a <hi>Refiners fire,</hi> and <hi>Fullers ſoap,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.4.</note> and with the <hi>breath of his lips</hi> he did <hi>ſlay the wicked. Iſ.</hi> 11.4.</p>
            <p>Such are the Teachers that a <hi>good conſcience</hi> loveth and delights in. But our age can no more endure this kind of preaching, then the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> could endure the <hi>ſhrill ſound of the Trumpet, ſounding louder and louder;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He.</hi> 12.19.</note> and that <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52020:40"/>fire,</hi> and that <hi>voice of words,</hi> which they deſired they might <hi>heare no more.</hi> Chriſts Miniſters now are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> (ſay they) their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine only legall; though indeed they trace Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their method, who firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Repentance</hi> to be <hi>preached,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lu.</hi> 24.47.</note> and then <hi>remiſſion</hi> of ſins to be <hi>promiſed:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> drawes all his doctrine unto theſe 2 heads, firſt <hi>repentance towards God;</hi> the ſecond <hi>faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.21.</note> Yet men are now become ſo tender, that they will not have their <hi>Dalilahs</hi> toucht, you may not come unto them, as the <hi>good Samaritan,</hi> with <hi>wine</hi> to ſearch and cleanſe, but only with <hi>ſmooth oyle</hi> to heale and comfort; it muſt be all the <hi>riches of Chriſt,</hi> and a naked <hi>faith in Chriſt.</hi> If you touch with <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> you are legall, and <hi>Phiſitions of no value.</hi> But let me tell ſuch as follow ſuch Doctors, their cauſe is dangerous; <hi>when the blind lead the blind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.16.</note> you can eaſily conclude what will follow. <hi>The leaders of this people cauſe them to erre, and they that are lead of them, are deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:52020:40"/>Wherefore would you be aſſured that your <hi>conſcience</hi> is a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> do not with <hi>Ahab</hi> hate <hi>Micaiah,</hi> nor with <hi>Ananias</hi> ſmite <hi>Paul,</hi> do not vilify thoſe <hi>whom God doth honour;</hi> I meane zealous, honeſt and conſciencious <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who labour in the word and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and are <hi>examples to the flock in faith and love, in ſpirit and purity;</hi> if you do, we are bold to challenge you for men of an <hi>evill conſcience,</hi> but on the other ſide if you honour them, as men <hi>ſent of God,</hi> and highly <hi>eſteeme them for their workes ſake,</hi> and readily <hi>obey</hi> their wholſome doctrine, <hi>following</hi> them as they <hi>follow Chriſt,</hi> you may then ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, we are aſſured <hi>we have a good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſt</hi> Note of good Conſcience is <hi>univerſall Obedience.</hi> This is an excellent diſtinguiſhing note between <hi>truth and error,</hi> a <hi>good</hi> and an <hi>evill conſcience.</hi> God calls for this, ſaying, <hi>in all things that I have commanded you, be circumſpect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>23.13.</hi> Caute eſtote <hi>1.</hi> magna</note> God will have <hi>conſcience</hi> to be <hi>good to all perſons,</hi> Act. 24.16. and <hi>good in all things,</hi> Heb. 13.18. and to be <hi>good at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52020:41"/>all times.</hi>
               <note place="margin">attentione. ſervate va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabl.</note> It muſt be our exerciſe <hi>daily to keep a conſcience void of offence both towards God and towards man.</hi> He that hath a <hi>good conſcience</hi> his heart is moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into <hi>obedience,</hi> his will is caſt into <hi>Gods will.</hi> He is ready to do what <hi>God commands,</hi> and to leave undone what <hi>God forbids.</hi> Like the ſlower that opens and ſhuts with the Sun. So it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to God and ſhuts to ſin. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to do Gods will on earth, as the Angels do it in heaven, <hi>readily, ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, conſtantly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now try our ſelves by this note, and we ſhall find a <hi>good conſcience</hi> to be very rare, we may <hi>run</hi> (with Jeremie) <hi>to and fro</hi> to find ſuch a man;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.1.</note> we may goe into many <hi>families, townes</hi> &amp; <hi>pariſhes</hi> &amp; <hi>perchance</hi> miſſe him at the laſt.</p>
            <p>The prophane and vitious will not owne ſuch <hi>good conſcience;</hi> and the Civill Juſtitia and formall Hyprocrite care not.</p>
            <p>Theſe two laſt have high conceits of themſelves, but yet upon tryall will be <hi>found too light.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52020:41"/>
            <p>Firſt the <hi>civill man</hi> thinks well of himſelfe becauſe he is kind unto his neighbour, defrauds no man, but payes every man to a penny, and as for the poor &amp; needy, he is open handed ready to ſupply their wants at all times: and therefore doubts not but his <hi>conſcience</hi> is very <hi>good,</hi> but let me tell thee thou <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill man,</hi> thou art much deceived, if thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> were <hi>good,</hi> thou wouldeſt be <hi>holy</hi> to God, as well as <hi>upright</hi> to man, how is it that thou art ſo ignorant in the things of God and of thine own ſalvation, that thou makeſt no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>prayer</hi> in thy Familie, of reading the <hi>Word,</hi> of hearing it preached unto thee: no conſcience of an <hi>Oath,</hi> of a <hi>lie,</hi> and of keeping the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> ſurelie if thy <hi>conſcience</hi> be not good to God as well as to man, it is void of goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>formall Hypocrite</hi> is as high, if not higher, in his conceits of ſelf worthineſſe, He is one that labours to know God and to ſerve him, both <hi>publikely</hi> in the Congregation, &amp; <hi>private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in his Familie, hee is a profeſſed oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52020:42"/>unto <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>prophanes</hi> and prayſeth God that he is <hi>not as other men</hi> and ſo concludes that he hath a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt tell thee thou Hyporite, thou art as much deceived as the former.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</note> The <hi>Grace of God that bringeth ſalvation teacheth thee</hi> to be <hi>righteous</hi> as well as <hi>holy.</hi> If thy conſcience be good, how isit that thou art ſo deceitfull in <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining;</hi> ſo falſe in <hi>promiſing;</hi> ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull in <hi>paying:</hi> what is thy <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt religion</hi> better then the civill mans <hi>irreligious honeſty,</hi> you both come ſhort of a <hi>good conſcience</hi> and if you thus perſiſt will come ſhort of heaven &amp; all true happineſſe, let me threfore adviſe you to beware of others harmes, look upon <hi>Saul, Jehu, Hered, and the high prieſts,</hi> Theſe in their owne eyes were very conſcionable men.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.34.</note> Saul will not have the people to <hi>ſin againſt the Lord in eating with the bloud:</hi> Jehu will be <hi>Zealous for God</hi> in rooting out <hi>Ahabs poſteritie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.26</note> Herod makes conſcience of his <hi>Oath</hi> to <hi>Herodias,</hi> the HIgh Prieſt will not put the <hi>price of bloud</hi> into the treaſury.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52020:42"/>
            <p>See and behold a Meſſe of <hi>Notorious Hypocrites,</hi> ahd theſe been ſyncere their <hi>conſciences</hi> would have been good to all, in all, and alwaies.</p>
            <p>If <hi>ſaul</hi> had truly made conſcience of <hi>beaſt bloud</hi> he would not have been ſo prodigall of <hi>mans bloud,</hi> as to deſtroy 85. <hi>of the Lords prieſts that wore the lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Ephod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Jehu</hi> had truly made conſcience of pulling downe <hi>Ahabs Idols,</hi> he would not have left <hi>Jeroboams Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Herod</hi> had truly made conſcience of an <hi>Oath,</hi> he would not ſo eaſilie have granted <hi>John Baptiſts head</hi> unto his Herodias.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>High prieſt</hi> had trulie made conſcienceof taking the <hi>price of bloud,</hi> they would not have beene ſo readie to give a <hi>price for bloud</hi> as 30 peices to <hi>Iudas</hi> to <hi>betray his Maſter,</hi> but as they <hi>ſowed,</hi> ſo they <hi>reaped:</hi> They ſowed <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>reaped ſhame,</hi> and ſo ſhall all that anſwer Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in parte but not in whole.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52020:43"/>
            <p>If therefore: thou wilt beapproved <hi>of God,</hi> approve thy ſelfe <hi>to God</hi> in an <hi>univerſall Obedience, be good to all,</hi> be <hi>good in all,</hi> or not <hi>good at all,</hi> and thus much of this firſt uſe namely the uſe of Triall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uſe, is for reproofe unto the ignorant and prophane, who though they never tryed, nor yet intend to try themſelves, by theſe fore-mentioned Notes or marks, yet will boldly tell you, they have a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But will you know upon what ground they build this bould Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>Anſwer: It is upon a very falſe ground, and upon a very <hi>ſandie foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> That is upon the ſtillneſſe and quietneſſe of their <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Though they ſweare, lye, ſteale, oppreſſe, be drunke, and act uncleaneſſe and all manner of villanie; yet their <hi>conſcience</hi> doth not moleſt or trouble them.</p>
            <p>They do not check, or ſay unto them <hi>what haſt thou done?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6.</note> and therefore are ready to <hi>bleſſe themſelves</hi> to be moſt happie, and to <hi>condemne others</hi> whoſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52020:43"/>
               <hi>conſciences</hi> do trouble them to be moſt unhappy.</p>
            <p>But let me tell ſuch, that Quietneſſe or unquietneſſe are no infallible cha\racters of a <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evill conſcience:</hi> poſſible it is that a <hi>quiet Conſcience</hi> may carrie a man <hi>merrilie to Hell,</hi> and on the other ſide an <hi>unquiet Conſcience</hi> may carrie a man <hi>crying to Heaven.</hi> The one may never dreame of Hell afore they fall into it, The other never be aſſured of Heaven before they have the poſſeſſion of it.</p>
            <p>The old world were <hi>eating and drinking,</hi> revelling and making merry, <hi>when the floud came and ſwept them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> Zimri and Coſbi in the very Act of uncleanneſſe, were <hi>thruſt through with a Iavelin,</hi> and how many in theſe <hi>unhappy warrs</hi> have ſuddenlie periſhed and come to a <hi>fearfull end,</hi> when they dreamed not of it. Their drunken health being their laſt draught, &amp; their blaſphemeous Oaths their laſt words: ſo that we may trulie ſay they went <hi>merrily to Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:52020:44"/>
            <p>Againe on the other ſide, if men profeſſing Chriſt may dye without aſſurance and yet be ſaved (as <hi>Mr Chambers</hi> in Leiceſter, who cryed out that he was damned,<note place="margin">Perkins Hilderſham</note> and <hi>Francis Spira</hi> who would change his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Cain, Sanl and Judas) If ſuch might be ſaved as ſome in Charity think, then may we ſay and that ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie that ſome go <hi>crying unto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore my Adviſe to ſuch, is not to preſume upon a ſtill and <hi>quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> but to ſee from whence this ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; quietneſſe ariſeth, if from a true knowledg of Gods holineſſe and their owne vileneſſe, if from a true ſight and ſence of thier ſin and an unfained hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for the ſame, with an Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods free pardon in Chriſt, then is their peace and quietneſſe of the right kind, ſuch a <hi>Quietneſſe</hi> as neither doth nor can accuſe, them but gives a Comfortable teſtimonie of their holy walking before God ſince their converſion.</p>
            <p>Examples of ſuch, we find in <hi>Obadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:52020:44"/>who told Elijah,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Kin. <hi>18.12.</hi> Heb. <hi>11.5.</hi> Hujuſmodi conſcientia eſt inſtarfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae alicujus quae qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>din dormit vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur eſſe cicur, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laedit, Sed excitata in bominem involat &amp; dilace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Sic con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiacau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriata, aeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritudine aliâ gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viore, vel ctiam morte appropin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quante exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taturà Deo, &amp; trucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta ſuâ immanitate homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Alſt. Thecl. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuum. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that he <hi>feared the Lord from his youth,</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> who before his <hi>tranſlation</hi> had from God more then an ordinary Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>that he pleaſed god,</hi> ſo <hi>Paul</hi> I <hi>Have lived</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in all good good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before God, untill this day.</hi> theſe had good Conſciences indeed, ſuch as ſpeak peace with Gods allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>But if thy quietneſſe or ſtilneſſe which is in thee, do ariſe out of an Ignorance of God and of thy ſelfe, not knowing the mind and will of God and how Croſſe their waies and workes have been unto the ſame. Or if out of impenitency, not regarding ſin, nor humbling thy ſelfe for ſin. Then let me tell thee thy conſcience is not good but evill, thy quiet conſcience is a <hi>ſleepie Conſcience,</hi> a dull and drowſie Conſcience, and if not timelie preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted will prove a dead, a <hi>ſeared</hi> &amp; a <hi>caute riſed conſcience,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. &amp; though for the preſentit ſleep like a churliſh maſtife and neither <hi>bite</hi> nor <hi>barke,</hi> yet at laſt it will be awakened and fly in thy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52020:45"/>face, and tare thee, as the Divell did the <hi>man in which he entred</hi> Mark. 9.22, <hi>He rent him and threw him into the fire. Belſhazer</hi> was <hi>drinking wine in Bowles:</hi> But there came out <hi>Fingers on the wall and his countenance changed,</hi> Dan. 5.5. When the eye of your conſcience ſhall be opened, and thou ſhalt ſee a <hi>diſmall hand-writing</hi> againſt thee, hell gaping, and the juſt Judge preparing Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for thee, what prodigious horror will ſurprize thee? hadſt thou a world of worlds in thy poſſeſſion, thou wouldſt count them of too ſmall Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue to purchaſe a freedome from theſe firſt fruits of Hell.</p>
            <p>As a member that is Benumb'd with ſleepe, is ſenleleſſe and ſeems to be voide of all life. But yet when it gathers blood and awakens againe, it Shoots and pricks, and feeles as big as Ten. So conſcience may be paſt feeling; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Remor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeleſſe, Stupid,</hi> like a member that is benumm'd, and hath no ſenſe in it (as the word ſignifies) like a dead man that feeles not the heavieſt Burden that is
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52020:45"/>laid on him. But when it is <hi>awakned,</hi> Oh that Infinite unexpreſſable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that will ſurround thy pretious ſoule! At thy <hi>Right hand,</hi> thy ſins will be accuſing thee. At thy <hi>Left hand</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Devills expecting thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder thee</hi> the fulneſſe of hell bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; <hi>Above thee</hi> an Angry Judg, and <hi>within thee</hi> hty Conſcience tormenting. So that to <hi>live</hi> will be a torment, to <hi>dye</hi> will be an Hell. Yea God himſelfe will rowſe it up, if not by his <hi>word</hi> as he did <hi>Ahabs Conſcience,</hi> or by his rod as he did <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> yet by his <hi>terrible preſence</hi> when thou ſhalt ſtand before his Tribunall, then ſhalt thou <hi>call unto the mountaines to fall upon thee, and the Hills to cover thee from the preſence of the Lord:</hi> Yea then ſhall thy <hi>conſcience</hi> like a vulture gnaw upon thy heart, and like a Scorpion ſting thy very ſoule, and that rigorouſlie, without <hi>Commsſeration:</hi> conſtantly, without <hi>intermiſſion:</hi> and continually, without <hi>ceſſation:</hi> then ſhalt thou feele that <hi>worme that never dyeth, and that fire
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52020:46"/>that never goeth out.</hi> Oh therefore do not content thy ſelfe which a falſe peace, but labour for the peace which God appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, <hi>give no reſt to thine eyes or ſlumber unto thine eye lids before</hi> thou haſt gotten a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> namely A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience both <hi>purified</hi> and <hi>pacified</hi> by the bloud and ſpirit of Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Uſe for Comfort to ſuch as have tried and upon a truetryall have found themſelves to be enriched with this <hi>precious Iewel namely a good conſcience,</hi> let ſuch magnifie God &amp; ſay, <hi>the Lord hath dealt moſt bountifullie with me,</hi> praiſed be his great Name <hi>for his uuſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable gift.</hi> Elkanah could ſay to Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah that he was <hi>better unto her then ten ſonnes.</hi> But thy <hi>good conſcience</hi> may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay to the that ſhe is better then ten thouſand ſonnes then a world of earthlie freinds, for under God and his Chriſt, <hi>conſcience</hi> is the friend of friends the trueſt, ſweeteſt, conſtanſt and moſt faithfull friend.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The trueſt Friend,</hi> which will deale moſt truly with thee, earthly Frinds come ſhort both in reproofes
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52020:46"/>and comforts, they doe what they do by halfe, ſpeak a little to thy face, but more behind thy back, and many times deale untruly with thee; when thou doeſt good, they will ſay thou doeſt evill, and when thou doeſt evill, They will ſay well done, but thy <hi>good conſcience</hi> will not do ſo, will not <hi>daub with untempered morter</hi> nor <hi>call good, evill,</hi> nor <hi>evill good;</hi> but will deal very plainly with thee, <hi>accuſing</hi> thee when thou doeſt ill, and ſo <hi>excuſing</hi> thee when thou doeſt well.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſweeteſt friend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> that will make thee ever merry, and <hi>alwaies rejoyce.</hi> to laugh under the whip, to <hi>ſing in the ſtocks,</hi> to joy even then when thy goods are ſpoyled, yea in the ſharpe tryalls to <hi>rejoyce that thou art accounted worthy to ſuffer for Chriſt</hi> and to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat thy Joy, thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> will feaſt thee, nor once or twiſe but every day, it will be a <hi>continuall feaſt</hi> unto thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The conſtanſt friend,</hi> In time of diſtreſſe, when carnall friends fayle thee, this will abide with thee. Art thou in diſgrace which men, hated tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52020:47"/>accuſed, condemned, do the Abjects mock thee, the <hi>drunkards make ſongs upon thee,</hi> do Beliaſte charge thee with lies and Falſities, doth <hi>Tertullus</hi> withall his Art render thee an odious and <hi>peſtilent fellow.</hi> Againe, do thy own friends account thee an hypocrite as <hi>Iobs friends</hi> did him, and the world value thee as the <hi>filth and of-ſcouring of all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 16.19.</note> yet comfort thy ſelfe in this; that thy <hi>teſtimony is on high,</hi> and thy witneſſe in heaven, yea thy witneſſe is on earth, in thine owne conſcience, ſay with Job, not with ſtanding all their ſpite and lies againſt me, <hi>I will hold faſt my righteouſneſſe and will not let it go,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 27.6.</note> 
               <hi>my conſcience ſhal not reproach me whilſt I live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The faithfull'ſt friend,</hi> that will help at a pinch, and when thou art in greateſt need; <hi>Job</hi> tells us that he had friends, but they were unfaithfull, They <hi>deceived him as a brook</hi> deceiveth the wearie and thirſtie Traveller, he comes unto it in Summer to quench his thirſt and then behold it is dried up:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52020:47"/>againe he ſeeks unto it in the Winter ſeaſon, and then behold it is frozen, ſo that he is ſtill diſappointed of his hope. Thus deale my unfaithfull friends with me ſaith Job, when I have moſt need of their help, then they faile me.<note place="margin">Job. 6.15.</note> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon compares ſuch to a <hi>broken Tooth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 25.19.</note> and a <hi>foot out of joynt,</hi> which will ſurely deceive ſuch as truſt unto them; for when they go to eate, their tooth will hinder them; or when to walke, their foot will paine them, and ſo to be of no uſe or profit unto them. But a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> is no ſuch <hi>falſe friend,</hi> no thou mayeſt truſt unto it in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt preſſures, in times of diſgrace, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, ſickneſſe, death, and judgment: when all forſake thee, then will thy <hi>conſcience</hi> like a <hi>faithfull Jonathan</hi> ſtand by thee.<note place="margin">Ruth. 1.17</note> 
               <hi>Ruth's</hi> reſolution to ſtick to <hi>Naomi</hi> in all changes was more then ordinary to tell her that <hi>nothing but death ſhould part them:</hi> But here behold a better freind, death ſhall not part thee and thy Conſcience, ſhe will be with thee in ſickneſſe and in health, in life and death, in judgment and before
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52020:48"/>Gods Tribunall. Therefore rejoice, and let thy God be ever magnified.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Uſe is to exhort all ſuch as have not this <hi>Heartejewell of a good conſcience,</hi> to labour above all things for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it. This is that <hi>unum neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium,</hi> though generally neglected. Every man voluntarily of himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires a good Wife, good Children, good Servants, good Cloathes, good hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yea all good; but as for a <hi>good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> which is worth all, and without which all theſe outward bleſſings will be but ſo many curſes unto us, yet alas how careleſſe are moſt in the getting of the one, how earneſt and laborious in the other. Let me therefore adviſe you in the firſt place to labour for a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> ſo ſhall all theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings be ſweetned unto you. Now that you may not be deceived in this <hi>rich commodity,</hi> I will briefly ſhew you what it is.</p>
            <p>A <hi>good conſcience</hi> is a conſcience both purified and paciſied;<note place="margin" type="RunSum">What a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>is.</hi>
               </note> miſtake me not, I deny not but that Conſcience may be good, if only <hi>purified:</hi> but it cannot be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52020:48"/>well compleated, except it be alſo <hi>paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> for without this latter, there is many a ſad ſoule ſo troubled, that they will not beleive they have what indeed they have, viz. a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi> They are ſo far from <hi>Pauls aſſurance</hi> of a good conſcience, that they rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive their conſciences to be very evill and defiled Therefore ſtrive to get them both, namely a conſcience truely <hi>parified,</hi> and truly <hi>pacified.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Meanes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now followes the meanes both to <hi>purify</hi> and <hi>pacify</hi> conſcience.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the purifying of <hi>conſcience,</hi> it is the part of every one profeſſing Chriſt, to conſider that his conſcience <hi>naturally is defiled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> and that there is a neceſſity of taking off this defilement, if we would be ſaved, namely the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, error, and hardneſſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wherewith it is polluted. The principall meanes are <hi>two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt means to effect it,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Principall meanes.</note> is the <hi>bloud of Chriſt:</hi> by this bloud we muſt have our <hi>hearts ſprinkled from an evill conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.22. &amp; 9.14.</note> This is a ſingular way to have our <hi>Conſciences purged from dead works
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52020:49"/>to ſerve the living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Meanes is the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt.</hi> This is that mundifying water menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>I will ſprinkle cleane water upon you, and ye ſhall be cleant from all your filthineſſe.</hi> Theſe two, Chriſts bloud and Chriſts ſpirit will cleanſe the fouleſt ſinner and the moſt defiledſt conſcience. Paul writing unto the Corinthians tells them what filthy creatures they were,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9.10.</note> namely <hi>Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Idolaters, effeminate, abuſers of themſelves with mankind, Theeves, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, Drunkards, Railers, Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,</hi> and then ſhewed them by what meanes they were cured and cleanſed, namely by the blood and ſpirit of Chriſt.<note place="margin">v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>But ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> This is the <hi>refiners fire and fullers ſope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> this is that <hi>hyſope</hi> which will <hi>make us as white as ſnow,</hi> yea <hi>more white then ſnow, Pſ.</hi> 51.7.</p>
            <p>Other meanes there are, which though not comparable to the firſt, yet as ſubſervient, are likewiſe requiſite
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52020:49"/>to this <hi>purifying of Conſcience,</hi> namely the Word, Faith, Repentance.<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Leſſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal meanes.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Word. <hi>Now are ye cleane</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>through the word that I have ſpoken unto you, John.</hi> 15.3. That is to ſay, the word accompanied with the power of my Spirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. So Faith is of a cleanſing nature, it will <hi>purge the heart and cleanſe the converſation, Act.</hi> 15.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And as for repentance, we find that when <hi>Judah</hi> had defiled her ſelfe with ſin, God calls her to repentance as a way of cleanſing. <hi>Waſh ye, make you cleane, put away the evill of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, learne to do well,</hi> and then <hi>though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 1.16.</note> Thus you ſee how a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed conſcience may be purified.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next followes how <hi>conſcience</hi> may be <hi>pacified.</hi> Conſider firſt of all what it is that troubles <hi>conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Meanes.</note> It muſt be one of theſe <hi>three,</hi> either <hi>ſin,</hi> or <hi>Sathan,</hi> or <hi>Gods anger.</hi> It was <hi>ſin</hi> that ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Paul, the <hi>law in his members that warred againſt the law of his mind,</hi> that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52020:50"/>ſo diſquieted him, that it made him to cry out,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24</note> 
               <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me.</hi> 2. It was <hi>Sathan</hi> that <hi>winnowed</hi> Peter, and <hi>withſtood</hi> Jehoſhus 3. <hi>Gods anger</hi> that ſo <hi>moleſted</hi> David, as to make him cry out, <hi>Lord rebuke me not in thy wrath, neither chaſten me in thy hot diſpleaſure, there is no ſoundneſſe in my fleſh becauſe of thine anger.</hi> Therefore unto ſuch as are troubled with the ſight of their <hi>ſin,</hi> the aſſaults of <hi>Sathan,</hi> or ſence of Gods <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> if their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences be unquiet becauſe of theſe, either one or all, be carefull in the uſe of ſuch meanes as God hath ordained for pacifying conſcience.</p>
            <p>Now that I may not be tedious, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what were the meanes to <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie conſcience,</hi> and thou ſhalt find the very ſame meanes will <hi>pacify conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told thee before that the bloud of Chriſt and the Spirit of Chriſt as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall. 2. The word, faith, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as leſſe principall. Theſe would make a defiled conſcience to become pure.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:52020:50"/>
            <p>So now I muſt tell thee againe to make thy conſcience quiet thou muſt have</p>
            <p n="1">1. The bloud of Chriſt. Paul tels us that Chriſt <hi>by the bloud of his Croſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.20</note> i. e. by his bloudy oblation made upon the croſſe, <hi>hath made peace and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all things.</hi> Now rightly to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Text, you muſt know that by ſin, heaven and earth were ſet at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the creatures in them: but by Chriſt there is unity ſet, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and man, but alſo betwixt men and the Angels that are in heaven, as alſo the creatures that are upon the earth, now if <hi>Chriſts bloud</hi> be ſuch a Catholicon to take off all enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween God and man, between men and Angels in heaven, men and creatures on earth, and to make peace, then let us acknowledge it an excellent means to pacify conſcience. This was typifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>bloud of the Paſcall lamb:</hi> where this bloud was <hi>ſprinkled upon any door-poſt,</hi> there was peace and ſecurity againſt the <hi>deſtroyer.</hi> So where the <hi>bloud of Chriſt is</hi> ſprinkled upon the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52020:51"/>ſoule, their conſcience is at peace, and hath ſecurity againſt all the remaining guilt and corruption of ſin, the rage of Sathan, &amp; danger of Gods diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>This bloud givves the ſoule all <hi>bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to enter in into the holieſt of all by a new and living way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.19.</note> and gives us aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance before God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Meanes to pacify conſcience is the ſpirit of Chriſt, As his bloud is the <hi>procuring cauſe, ſo his ſpirit the producing cauſe.</hi> For this cauſe Chriſt and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt are called by one and the ſame name, becauſe their end and buſineſſe is the ſame, namely to procure peace to the ſoule. They both are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Advocates,</hi> Chriſt is our Advocate and and the ſpirit is Gods Advocate. Chriſt is our Advocate to the father to procure us peace: The ſpirit againe is Gods advocate to us to produce peace. As the one prevailes with God for granting peace, ſo the other prevailes with us to entertaine peace. See this cleared in 1 Joh: 2.1. <hi>If any man ſin we have a Paraclete with the father Jeſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi> Here
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52020:51"/>Chriſt is our advocate: againe Joh. 14.16. <hi>I will pray the father and he ſhall give you another Paraclete.</hi> In this place the holy Ghoſt is Gods advocate, ſo you plainly ſee how the bloud and ſpirit of Chriſt muſt make up this true and full peace. Now for the cauſes or meanes leſſe principall and ſubſervient, as the <hi>word, faith, repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt the <hi>word,</hi> it is a <hi>word of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> and pacification. Thus Peter to Cornelius and his company tells them, <hi>ye know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the word which God hath ſent to the children of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.36</note> 
               <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching peace by Jeſus Chriſt which is Lord of all.</hi> Now as the Scripture in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall may be ſaid to be a word of peace, ſo more eſpecially the Goſpell: This is called the word of peace. The Author of it the <hi>Prince of peace.</hi> The miniſter the <hi>Meſſenger of peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> and his preaching the goſpell, the <hi>miniſtry of reconcitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18.</note> yea as one ſaith it is Gods procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and our Charter of peace, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the largeſt conceſſions of peace. It is Gods act of oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52020:52"/>and his act of indemnity. <hi>Scheffeeld on conſe: p.</hi> 42.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Meanes of pacifying conſcience is <hi>faith.</hi> As the <hi>conſcience</hi> cannot ſpeak peace with Gods allowance before it be purged, ſo not peace after it is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged without faith; This is a grace that will doe both, i. e. purify and pacify.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That faith will purify is cleer, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Faith purgeth the heart and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the converſation.</hi> 2. That it will alſo pacify, this appeares <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Being juſtifyed by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Peace is the daughter of faith: This is that <hi>Dove</hi> that brings an <hi>Olive branch of peace</hi> in its mouth, aed preſents God a pacified and reconciled father unto us. O how ſweet is that peace which faith breeds? It is a Chriſtians heaven upon earth. A bunch of Grapes that growes on the true Vine, joy in life, peace at death, proſperity in adverſity, ſtaffe in affliction, ankere in deſperation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third and laſt ſubſervient
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52020:52"/>meanes is <hi>Repentance.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us <hi>our conſciences</hi> muſt be <hi>purged from dead workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.14</note> and we muſt have <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead workes.</hi> We muſt ſtill acknowledge that it is the bloud of Chriſt that muſt <hi>purge our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from dead workes,</hi> and ſo worke peace; yet know this, that this peace is not wrought in our apprehenſion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we feele this faith without further act. Therefore to our faith muſt be joined repentance, though not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our peace, yet for the, feeling of this peace.</p>
            <p>Let us now then breifly enumerate the cauſes principle and leſſe principle. 1. Chriſts bloud procuring. 2. Chriſts ſpirit producing. 3. His word proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. 4. Faith aſſuming. 5. Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance declaring and evidencing. All theſe in their order, not in a way of <hi>coordination,</hi> but in a way of <hi>ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> do effect the ſweet <hi>peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which paſſeth all underſtanding, Phil.</hi> 4.7. And is the ſweeteſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that ever accompanied man in this vale of mortality.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:52020:53"/>
            <p>Hitherto of the <hi>goodneſſe of Conſcience</hi> and how it becomes good, namely by the bloud and ſpirit of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is both purified and pacified.</p>
            <p>In the next place I muſt commend unto you theſe 3 things as ſpecially to be minded and endeavoured by you.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Having</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Holding</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Well uſing</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt let it be your ſpeciall care to have this <hi>good conſcience,</hi> and that you may have it take theſe few directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be ſenſeable of the want of it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit naturally we are all deſtitute of this jewell, yet very few complaine for want of it. Some are <hi>pure in their owne eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30.12.</note> yet were never <hi>purged from their filthineſſe,</hi> their <hi>conſciences</hi> as defiled as ever. Others openly profane and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that <hi>adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt,</hi> yet when a curſe is pronounced againſt them, they will <hi>bleſſe themſelves</hi> ſaying, <hi>we ſhall have peace:</hi> I muſt ſay to ſuch, they are <hi>whole &amp; need not the Phyſician.</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:52020:53"/>Thele are not as yet in a capacity of receiving this bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>I</hi> adviſe you, firſt to ſee the filthineſſe of your <hi>conſciences,</hi> how defiled with ignorance, error and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe: and having ſeen it, with the <hi>leper</hi> confeſſe it, and ſay <hi>Maſter, I am uncleane, I am uncleane:</hi> when thy diſeaſe is knowne, the cure is halfe wrought,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> therefore <hi>I</hi> ſay by all meanes to ſee how <hi>thy ſoule and conſcience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Seek out an able <hi>Phyſician</hi> that can cure thee, thinke not to find him here on earth, thou muſt go to heaven for him, it is God that firſt <hi>made</hi> thy <hi>conſcience,</hi> and he alone it is that can <hi>remake</hi> it: and therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe thy ſelfe unto him, humbly and faithfully acknowledging his power, and in the <hi>lepers</hi> phraſe expreſſe the deſire of thy heart and ſay, <hi>Maſter if thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane.</hi> And to quicken thee in this, <hi>I</hi> will ſay unto thee, as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> unto the <hi>blind man, go he calleth thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 10.49.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:52020:54"/>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſts invitation; <hi>Come unto me ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> All ye that more and more feel the burden of ſin, and can find no way to remove it, come you all to me, and I will eaſe you of your bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of ſin paſt, Pſ: 32.1, and free you from ſervitude of it hereafter. <hi>Sin ſhall not have dominion over you. Rom.</hi> 6.14. Therefore as <hi>blind Bartimeus,</hi> when Chriſt <hi>called him,</hi> forthwith caſt off his garment, roſe up and <hi>went</hi> to Chriſt; ſo thou who haſt an <hi>evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> make no delay, ſhake off all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments and run to Chriſt the true <hi>Phiſitian,</hi> and he will heale thee of thy diſeaſe, and give thee a pure and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>conſcience.</hi> There is <hi>water</hi> enough in <hi>Iordan;</hi> there is <hi>balme</hi> enopugh in <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead</hi> to poure into your wounds. And there is a <hi>Phiſitian</hi> there too, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires thee to come, and will heale thee <hi>without money or moneyes worth.</hi> Tis but <hi>looking on this brazen ſerpent</hi> and be whole.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Motive. His promiſe is to cure thee, he hath ſaid he will give thee <hi>on heart,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52020:54"/>put a new ſpirit into thee, take away thy ſtony heart out of thy fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 11.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>and give thee an heart of fleſh.</hi> Now what is this leſſe then to cure thy ſoule and <hi>conſcience,</hi> therefore thou mayeſt boldly go unto the Lord, plead the covenant between God and thee, tell him thou haſt it to ſhew under his hand, and ſo hold him to his promiſe. Lord thou haſt ſaid thou wilt give me a new heart, a new <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> therefore Lord <hi>create in me a new heart and renew a pure conſcience within me, let old things be done away and let all things become new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Direction is to obſerve what thy <hi>Phiſitian</hi> ſhall adviſe thee, his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are plainly ſet downe in his large Phiſick book, namely the <hi>book of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> there thou ſhalt find what thy diſeaſe is, the nature and ſymptomes of it, the meanes to cure it alſo, what diet thou muſt keep in the time of thy diſeaſe to be freed from it, and what diet afterwards to prevent a relapſe.</p>
            <p>Take heed therefore when thy <hi>great Phiſitian</hi> hath adviſed thee what meanes to uſe to take off this <hi>leprouſy</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:52020:55"/>from thy ſoule. Doe not ſlight it as <hi>Naaman</hi> did <hi>Eliſha's</hi> advice about the <hi>leprouſy</hi> of his body: when he adviſed him to <hi>waſh in Jordan</hi> and be cured, the text ſaith he was wroth,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.9.10.</note> preferring his owne <hi>waters of Abanah and Pharpar rivers of Damaſcus</hi> as better then all the <hi>waters of Iſrael.</hi> Take heed bee not wiſer then thy Doctor, <hi>credas medico ut valeas,</hi> follow his directions and thou ſhalt be healed. <hi>Eate</hi> and <hi>live, waſh</hi> and be <hi>cleane.</hi> Thus far by way of <hi>preparative,</hi> proceed we now unto the <hi>Phyſick</hi> it ſelfe, in which we find many ſimples compounded, as Naturals and Spirituals <hi>added.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are to adde light to light, i. e. the light of <hi>Scripture</hi> unto the light of <hi>Nature,</hi> without knowledge the <hi>conſcience</hi> cannot be good, but as a blind man drinke poiſon as ſoon as wholſome liquor, and ſtand as ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the brinke of a deep dungeon, as upon a broad pavement, and why, becauſe he ſeeth not the venome of the one, nor yet the danger of the other. Even ſo the blind <hi>conſcience drinks ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52020:55"/>as water,</hi> and ſtands feareleſly upon the brinke of hell, without any fear of falling into it, and all becauſe he ſeeth not the vileneſſe of the one, nor yet the miſcheife of the other, into which he runneth, therefore adde I ſay unto the light of <hi>nature</hi> the light of <hi>ſcripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Adde bloud to bloud, i. e. the <hi>bloud of Chriſt,</hi> to thy <hi>ſin-bleeding ſoule,</hi> this is that bloud which muſt cure thee and no other bloud can do it. 1. Beaſts bloud will nto heale thy <hi>conſcience, the bloud of buls</hi> and <hi>goats</hi> cannot purge away ſin. 2. Mans bloud will not as the <hi>bloud of Abel,</hi> or the bloud of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</hi> 3. Thine owne bloud will not cure thee, Saul having an <hi>evill conſcience</hi> might thinke to eaſe him ſelfe by <hi>falling on his owne ſword,</hi> and ſhedding his owne bloud; but alas this will not cure but kill. Ther's nothing can cure our ſick polluted <hi>conſciences,</hi> but only <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the poole of Betheſda.</hi> There is nothing can make us <hi>white,</hi> but the <hi>bloud of the lamb.</hi> It is Chriſts <hi>bloud</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;<note place="margin">Zach. 13.</note> this is that <hi>fountaine for ſin and for
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52020:56"/>uncleaneſſe;</hi> this is the bloud that muſt <hi>cleanſe thee from all ſin,</hi> 1 John 1.7, 8. See therefore thou adde unto thy blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſoule this <hi>precious blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Adde ſpirit unto ſpirit, i. e. unto thy ſpirit Gods ſpirit. When <hi>Gods ſpirit</hi> comes into <hi>thy ſpirit,</hi> it will not only regenerate thy ſpirit, but <hi>witneſſe with thy ſpirits</hi> that thou art healed, and make thee with a joyfull voice to <hi>cry out Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba father,</hi> Rom. 8.16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Adde faith to faith; unto thy <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall faith</hi> an <hi>applicative faith,</hi> thou then wilt not only beleive that theſe former ſimples and ingredients thus compounded, and as it were mixed, will cure an <hi>evill conſcience,</hi> but will boldly ſay, my evill <hi>conſcience</hi> by theſe meanes is purged and quieted. Where theſe principles and ſimples are thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and happily joined together, there is a perfect cure; the <hi>evill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> is become a <hi>good conſceence,</hi> the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed</hi> conſcience a <hi>purged</hi> conſcience; the <hi>troubled</hi> conſcience, a <hi>peaceable</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: thou art made whole, therfore as our Saviour unto the <hi>Adultereſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:52020:56"/>when ſhe had received merecy, gave her this caveat, <hi>to ſin no more:</hi> ſo ſay I to thee that haſt a pure and peaceable <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> go <hi>ſin no more,</hi> but obſerve thy <hi>Phyſitians rules</hi> in keeping a good diet: be <hi>holy</hi> to God, <hi>upright</hi> to man, &amp; <hi>ſober</hi> in thy ſelfe; if not, thou wilt fall back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine old diſeaſe, &amp; ſo thy condition will be more deſperate then ever.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>preſervatives,</hi> that conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may keep its purity and peace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Abſtaine from all appearances of evill.</hi> Account no ſin little, but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that a little leake may ſinke a ſhip, and one ſpark of fire may burne a city, it was but a wanton glance at firſt in <hi>David,</hi> when he looked on <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> but if you mark it, many <hi>ſins</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſorrowes</hi> followed upon that glance of his, ſo that which James ſpeaketh is here moſt true, <hi>behold how great a flame a little fire kindleth,</hi> therefore abſtame from the appearance of ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beware of intimacy with any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly perſon, take heed whom thou makeſt thy companion, the ſweeteſt diſpoſitions are ſooneſt ſowred by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:52020:57"/>ſociety, <hi>wicked Ahab</hi> is no fit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for <hi>godly Jehoſhaphat,</hi> nor <hi>Cerinthus</hi> (the Heretick) for <hi>John</hi> the Divine. Take heed of ſuch as are either <hi>erroneous</hi> in judgment, or <hi>vitious</hi> in converſation, wilt thou joine with thoſe that are enimies unto God? doeſt thou not know that one diſeaſed ſheep may infect an whole flock, ſo on corrupt man may corrupt a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: as we find in <hi>Alexander,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus, Philetus, Phigellus, Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines,</hi> and others, whoſe word did eat as doth a <hi>Canker,</hi> which if not ſeaſonably prevented will grow incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>The Originall word is <hi>gangrene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which ſignifies to eate, as the diſeaſe called a <hi>wolfe</hi> or a <hi>canker</hi> doth, which conſumeth not only the part where it is, but ſpreadeth farther in the fleſh. Such is the Nature of Hereticall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, if it be not ſtopt in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning &amp; cured by ſolid confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Eccleſiaſticall cenſures, upon thoſe that are obſtinate; it will ſpread far, and run over the whole body of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52020:57"/>the Church. Beware of ſuch, <hi>a man that is an Heretick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject: knowing that he that is ſuch, is ſubverted, and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelfe,</hi> i. e. convinced in his owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> that he ſhuts his eyes againſt the light, and reſiſteth and oppoſeth the known truth.</p>
            <p>The like I ſay for prophane and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons;</hi> though they <hi>entice thee, conſent thou not:</hi> and if they ſay, come with us, or be one of us, oh <hi>come not into the way of ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.10</note> 
               <hi>nor enter into the counſell of the ungodly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3.34</note> leſt thou <hi>ſit in the ſeat of the ſcorner,</hi> and at laſt become a <hi>ſcorne</hi> and a <hi>deriſion</hi> unto God and the godly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In doubtfull things take the ſureſt and ſafeſt way. All men have <hi>fleſh,</hi> and ſo conſequently <hi>error</hi> in them. Great differences ariſe in things practicall, one holds recreations on the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and another denies it: This man for <hi>uſury,</hi> that man againſt it; ſome ſay <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Troth</hi> are no Oathes, others will tell thee that they
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52020:58"/>are more then <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay.</hi> The Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude are for <hi>Cards, Dice, drinking of healths,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.37.</note> 
               <hi>long haire in men, and naked backs and breaſts in women,</hi> but the feweſt and wiſeſt are againſt all theſe. Judge thou therefore which is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt way, to uſe all theſe, or to refuſe them, heare what the Spirit tells thee, <hi>abſtaine from all appearance of evill: have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them.</hi> Doubtleſſe it will be ſafer for thee to deny thy ſelfe in <hi>forbearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.11.</note> then to take liberty in <hi>uſing</hi> them. Give no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to <hi>tender conſciences,</hi> but follow <hi>Paul,</hi> who was ſo wary of giving of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to Gods people, that even in things lawfull he would deny himſelfe, reſolving to <hi>eate no fleſh while the world ſtandeth, rather then to make his brother to offend</hi> (i. e.) to put a ſtumbling block before him,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.13.</note> or give an occaſion of ſin unto him. Wherefore walke on ſure ground, and be warranted from God for what thou doeſt. <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:52020:58"/>pure, lovely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any vertue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>if any praiſe, thinke on theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Take heed of falſe and <hi>phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Teachers,</hi> who boaſt of the <hi>ſpirit of</hi> God, when it is only their owne <hi>proud and lying ſpirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 13.3</note> They are <hi>fooliſh prophets that follow their owne ſpirit and have ſeen nothing,</hi> i. e. they do medle with <hi>prophecying</hi> of their owne proper moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being driven thereunto by their owne <hi>carnall affection,</hi> and declare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their owne vaine <hi>imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>frothy inventions.</hi> They would be accounted Phyſicians for ſick ſoules and wounded <hi>conſciences,</hi> but as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith they are <hi>Phyſicians of no value.</hi> For they <hi>heale the hurt of Gods people ſlightly, ſaying, peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>when there is no peace:</hi> they preach generally freedome and liberty, as freedome from <hi>confeſſion</hi> of ſin, and freedome to the <hi>commiſſion</hi> of ſin, but whilſt they thus preach <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> unto others, <hi>they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption,</hi> beware of ſuch: And beg of God <hi>Paſtors according to his owne heart, that may feed you with
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:52020:59"/>wiſdome and true underſtanding, whoſe lips may preſerve knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jere. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ye may ſack it at their mouth,</hi> who may be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples unto the flock in life and doctrine, faith and love, ſpirit and purity. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> could glory ſhe had ſuch Prophets ſuch Paſtors, and bleſed be God ſhe can yet ſay ſhe hath ſuch ſtill; true it is they lie under a <hi>cloud,</hi> but it is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares ſince that they were highly eſteemed, thought <hi>worthy of double honour,</hi> and conſulted with upon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of greateſt importment both in Church and State: yea <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>People invited them to come into Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> namely <hi>London,</hi> to help on the great worke of <hi>Reformation:</hi> but now are caſt aſide as <hi>of no value,</hi> and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accounted <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Kingdome of Chriſt, and to the power and purity of the Goſpel. A ſudden and ſtrange change, but we will lay it upon that <hi>envious one,</hi> whoſe rage is ſpecially againſt Gods <hi>faithfull Miniſters.</hi> You therefore that love a <hi>good conſcience</hi> make much of ſuch, and have them <hi>in high eſteeme for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:52020:59"/>their works ſake,</hi> becauſe it is the Lords.</p>
            <p>Thus far of <hi>having:</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. Holding</note> now followes the <hi>holding</hi> of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Theſ. 5.2.</note> The Spirit of God doth frequently preſſe us to this <hi>holding. Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good,</hi> i. e. try ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly all <hi>doctrines</hi> concerning <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>manners,</hi> and as thou findeſt them ſound and ſaving, ſo <hi>hold</hi> them.<note place="margin">Tit. 1.8, 9</note> Againe <hi>hold faſt the faithfull word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>hold faſt your Profeſſion, hold faſt till I come, hold faſt leſt another take thy crowne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.11.</note> i. e. the honour and glory promiſed to ſuch as ſhall perſevere. So ſay I, (<hi>ye not I,</hi> but the ſpirit of God) <hi>hold faith,</hi> and a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. yea above all <hi>hold</hi> theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hold</hi> againſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries that would <hi>withhold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> 1. R. Becauſe the labour is as great in <hi>holding</hi> as <hi>having, non minor eſt virtus quàm quaerere, parta tueri.</hi> It coſt <hi>Paul</hi> deare to get a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> and ſo it did to <hi>hold it.</hi> Twas his daiely exerciſe to <hi>keep a good conſcience, void of offence toward God and man.</hi> Act. 24.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. R. Becauſe many have <hi>made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:52020:60"/>of <hi>conſcience</hi> as <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> who giving the reines to a licentious courſe of life againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of their owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> God puniſhed them accordingly, by taking away the light of his ſpirit, that in the middeſt of their courſe they ſhould loſe their moſt precious ſpiritual <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe,</hi> and be drowned in error and hereſy,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.19, 20.</note> as thoſe who in a <hi>ſea-tempeſt</hi> ſuffer <hi>ſhip-wrack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. R. Becauſe the <hi>world</hi> cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> as we may ſee in <hi>Zedekiah</hi> his behaviour toward <hi>Micai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> and <hi>Paſhur</hi> toward <hi>Ieremie,</hi> how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civilly and rudely do theſe men carry themſelves,<note place="margin">1 King. 22, 24.</note> 
               <hi>Zedekiah</hi> he ſmites <hi>Michai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah on the cheeke,</hi> impudently and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully before the King and whole aſſembly; ſaying unto him, <hi>which way went the ſpirit of the Lord from me to ſpeake to thee?</hi> pretending that <hi>himſelfe</hi> had the ſpirit of God, and thereupon inferres that <hi>Micaiah</hi> had it not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it could not be ſhewed how it ſhould paſſe from the one unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So <hi>Paſhur ſmites Ieremie, and puts
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:52020:60"/>him in the ſtocks,</hi> and herein ſhewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a prime inſtrument of Sathan, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrating that againſt the Lords <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> which neither <hi>King,</hi> nor <hi>Princes,</hi> nor <hi>people</hi> durſt formerly attempt.<note place="margin">Jer. 20.2.</note> Thus <hi>Amaziah the prieſt with Amos,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>them that ſtood by to ſmite Paul on the mouth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Am. 7.10.</note> what was the cauſe of this their rage and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? had theſe men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted any groſſe offence? ſurely no; it was only the <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of their <hi>conſcience</hi> that did thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate their rage againſt them. Theſe were the faithfull <hi>ſervants of the Lord,</hi> that boldly declared the mind and <hi>will of God</hi> unto them, as in <hi>conſcience</hi> they were bound, and therefore could not endure them. There is an irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Antipathy</hi> between the men of the <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> of God, they can no ſooner mingle, then <hi>oyle</hi> and <hi>water;</hi> nor better agree then <hi>light</hi> and <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The Spirit that is in you the world cannot receive,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, John 14.17. they are convinced that they are conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious men, but as they were wont to ſay in former times, CAIUS SEIUS <hi>was
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:52020:61"/>a good man, but he was a Chriſtian.</hi> So now,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caius Seius</hi> bonus vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus.</note> ſuch are good men, but they are too ſtrict, too conſcientious, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot away with them. Thus you ſee how the men of this world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. R. Becauſe the <hi>Devill</hi> doth more envie a <hi>good conſcience</hi> then any other thing. Let men be never ſo high in <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> great in <hi>wealth,</hi> abound in <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>policy,</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> diſlikes it not, he knowes the better how to make uſe of them to ſerve his turne, as we ſind in <hi>Pharaoh, Zenacherib, Achitophel, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> and others: who in their <hi>Pomp</hi> and <hi>power</hi> were higher then their <hi>brethren by head and ſhoulders,</hi> and accordingly more active and ready to do his work: That man I ſay have abundance of theſe outward things, it doth not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet but pleaſe Satan; But when any have a good; a pure and a tender <hi>conſcience,</hi> this madds the Divel and makes him to ſet all his inſtruments on worke to bereave ſuch of their <hi>Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jswell,</hi> namely a <hi>good conſcience;</hi> we
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:52020:61"/>may ſee this in <hi>Luther,</hi> his pure <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> did vex both <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Devill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melchior Adam in vitâ Luth.</note> what would not they have done to have ſtrangled his <hi>conſcience,</hi> if <hi>honour, wealth, preferment,</hi> or any outward thing could have prevailed, the <hi>Pope</hi> would have collated all theſe upon him, but one tells the <hi>Pope,</hi> that all theſe would not doe, for (ſaith he) <hi>Germana illa beſtia aurum non curat, that German beaſt</hi> (meaning <hi>Luther</hi>) <hi>will not be won by any or all of theſe.</hi> And at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time when great gifts were ſent to him, he refuſed them with this moſt brave and excellent ſpeech. <hi>Valdè pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatus ſum me nolle ſic ſatiari ab eo: I did earneſtly proteſt that God ſhould not put me off with theſe things.</hi> Meaning that he would not be ſatisfyed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing here below: his ſpirit was too noble to be tempted with Gold to the loſſe of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> Here then you ſee what need there is to <hi>hold a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> yea to hold it faſt, as <hi>Cynegrius</hi> his ſhip, with tooth and naile.</p>
            <p>Meanes how to <hi>hold</hi> a <hi>good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:52020:62"/>
            <p n="1">1. Get more light into thy <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> thou haſt already a double light, namely the <hi>light of nature</hi> and the <hi>light of Scripture,</hi> be carefull to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe this latter light. There is and hath been many a tender hearted Chriſtian who for want of <hi>Scripture light</hi> hath neglected many a good duty, and ſo loſt much ſweet ſolace and comfort, which they might have enjoyed in the performance of it As for example; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>'Fatriarchs</hi> for want of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light fell into that ſin of <hi>Polygamy,</hi> not underſtanding that place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Lev. 18.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take a wife to her Siſter to vex her.</hi> They under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this only of a <hi>Naturall</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and not of a <hi>Nationall</hi>) took unto themſelves the liberty of many wives, and ſo it is amongſt us to this day, for want of a greater light, not only what we ought to do is <hi>omitted,</hi> but often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times what we ought not to do is <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed,</hi> therefore labour for a greater light in thy <hi>underſtanding, let the word of God dwell in you plenteouſly.</hi> hide it within you even in the middeſt of your heart.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:52020:62"/>
            <p n="2">2. Beware of multiplicity of <hi>imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> be not <hi>a buſie body in other mens matters,</hi> or as the Proverb, <hi>deſire not to have an Oare in every mans Boat,</hi> ſuch buſie perſons are great enimies to their owne <hi>conſciences,</hi> and by their <hi>ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> wit and <hi>needleſſe activity,</hi> their heads are filled with <hi>Queries,</hi> and their <hi>hearts</hi> with <hi>cares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Beware of unruly <hi>paſſions</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly <hi>affections:</hi> theſe if let looſe are like wild <hi>horſes,</hi> which will never leave running till they have unhorſed their <hi>Riders,</hi> and given them <hi>a dangerous,</hi> if not a <hi>deadly</hi> fall. Thus <hi>Sauls</hi> paſſion towards <hi>'David,</hi> and <hi>Ammons</hi> affection to his Siſter <hi>Thamar,</hi> they were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, ſo diſorderly, that they made them loſe all working of <hi>conſcience,</hi> dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them headlong into <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>Shame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Beware of wounding <hi>conſcience</hi> afreſh with any allowed ſin: if thou be healed, <hi>ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing do befall thee. Relapſes</hi> are very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; <hi>Bones,</hi> twiſe broken augment the paine, and difficilitate the cure: ſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:52020:63"/>ſhalt thou find in <hi>conſcience.</hi> Hath thy <hi>conſcience</hi> been formerly wounded, and hath God in mercy cured thee? take heed of wounding it againe, leſt thy paine be double, and thy cure made more difficult, and thou find in thy ſelfe no difference between thee and a reprobate. Oh therefore take heed of every ſin, free thy <hi>conſcience</hi> every day from the burden of ſin, know that a pure <hi>conſcience</hi> can better beare a <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> of miſery, then a <hi>mole hill of ſin;</hi> if thou carefully uſe theſe meanes, thou ſhalt be ſure not only to <hi>have</hi> but alſo to <hi>hold</hi> a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told you formerly of 3 things which were eſpecially to be minded &amp; endeavoured by us. 1 The <hi>having of a good conſcience.</hi> 2. The <hi>holding</hi> of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> 3. The <hi>uſing</hi> or exerciſing of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> Of the <hi>having</hi> and <hi>hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> we have already ſpoken: now in the laſt place we are to ſpeak of the <hi>exerciſing</hi> of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> having ſpoken of the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of his <hi>conſcience</hi> and a aſſurance of the ſame leſt any ſhould judge him a vaine
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:52020:63"/>
               <hi>Boaſter,</hi> and that it was ſome <hi>phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> opinion or <hi>fanaticall</hi> viſion, and no well grounded aſſertion, he goes to cleare it by 4 ſound Characters of a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> ſet down in the latter part of my <hi>Text,</hi> I know I have a good conſcience, and upon this ground I ſtand firme, becauſe <hi>I am willing in all things to live</hi> (or walke) <hi>honeſtly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. His will (he ſaith <hi>he is willing</hi>) 2. The extent or latitude of his will <hi>(in all things.)</hi> 3. The conſtancy of his will, <hi>(to walke or live.)</hi> 4. The ſyncerity of his will, <hi>(to walke honeſtly.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhall come to <hi>Paul,</hi> as the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaying, <hi>what doeſt thou do, that we may beleive thee,</hi> thou talkeſt much of the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of thy <hi>conſcience,</hi> whereby doeſt thou demonſtrate the ſame, that we may beleive thee: to ſuch <hi>Paul</hi> readily anſwers, I am ſure of a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> for <hi>I am willing in all things to live honeſtly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Character of his <hi>good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is his <hi>will;</hi> you may not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his <hi>naturall will,</hi> for this being corrupt and carnall cannot will any
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:52020:64"/>thing pleaſing unto God, it being like himſelfe altogether abominable. Mans <hi>naturall will</hi> is to pleaſe himſelfe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers like himſelfe, but not to pleaſe God, it is <hi>not ſubject unto the will of God, neither indeed can be.</hi> Examples hereof are many.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt in <hi>Sauls Courtiers,</hi> they had a will to pleaſe <hi>themſelves</hi> but not God, <hi>our tongues are our owne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 12.4.</note> ſay they, <hi>and we will ſpeake,</hi> we have ſtill power and liberty to ſpeak and are able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to whatſoever we take in hand. The like we find in thoſe <hi>worldlings</hi> that <hi>James</hi> mentions,<note place="margin">Jam. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>to day or to morrow we will go into ſuch a city and continue there a year, and buy and ſeſt, and get gaine:</hi> Thus you ſee their will was wholly to pleaſe themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their will is to pleaſe <hi>others</hi> like themſelves: as <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 15.15.</note> how willing was he to pleaſe the prophane <hi>multitude</hi> in <hi>releaſing Barrabas and delivering Jeſus to be cruciſied.</hi> So was <hi>Foelix</hi> very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pleaſe the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and to give them all content that ſo they might not follow him with complaints, his will
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:52020:64"/>was to <hi>leave Paul bound.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24 27.</note> Thus you ſee what our owne <hi>wills</hi> are, very corrupt, apt to pleaſe our ſelves, but not God; and therefore ſuch a <hi>will</hi> can be no character of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know therefore that <hi>Pauls</hi> will in the <hi>Texe</hi> is better principled, a <hi>will</hi> ſanctified by the ſpirit of God, a <hi>will</hi> freely willing to do what God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Such a will we find in <hi>Joſhus,</hi> who aſſembling the <hi>Tribes at Shechem</hi> and declaring a briefe hiſtory of Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits towards tehm,<note place="margin">Joſh. 2.4 14.</note> even <hi>from the daies of Terah,</hi> exhorteth them to the <hi>ſervice of this God,</hi> and to renew their <hi>covenant</hi> with him, ſaying, <hi>heare the Lord and ſerve him in ſyncerity and in truth, put away the Gods that your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſerved, and ſerve the Lord:</hi> If your <hi>wills</hi> bind not to the true God, know yee that my <hi>will</hi> doth; I am reſolved that <hi>I and mine houſhould ſhall ſerve the Lord.</hi> Such a will was in <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 119: 106.</note> 
               <hi>I have vowed and will performe it to keep thy righteous judgments.</hi> And by this <hi>will</hi> came <hi>Paul</hi> to be aſſured of the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of <hi>conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:52020:65"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
               </label> Now Beloved, let us examine our ſelves whether there be ſuch a <hi>will</hi> and willingneſſe in us as was in <hi>Paul</hi> to pleaſe God. Me thinks I heare you ſay, I would pleaſe God; you ſay you would, but tell me is it the very bent of your heart and your conſtant endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſo to doe? if not, I muſt tell you, your <hi>woulding</hi> is but a <hi>vaine wiſhing</hi> and nothing worth. There is not the <hi>pooreſt</hi> perſon, but he would be <hi>rich,</hi> the verieſt <hi>Bankrupt,</hi> but he would be <hi>thrifty,</hi> nor the <hi>vileſt</hi> perſon, but he will ſay, he would be <hi>honeſt;</hi> but will you beleive ſuch, becauſe they ſay they would be ſuch, when you ſee the bent of their heart and courſe of life is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? ſurely no; neither may we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive ſuch to have a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> which have only a <hi>woulding</hi> without <hi>endeavouring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Character of a <hi>good conſcience</hi> appeares in the extent of his will; Paul doth not barely ſay: that he is willing in this or that particular to pleaſe God, or with <hi>Herod willing to doe many things,</hi> but he is <hi>willing in all
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:52020:65"/>things,</hi> i.e. in all duties divine &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane of piety and charity. This uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Obedience is an excellent diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing note between <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>error,</hi> yea between a <hi>good</hi> and an <hi>evill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cauti e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtote. <hi>i.e.</hi> magnam attentione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſervate.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. God requires it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.13. ſaying unto his people, <hi>In all things that I have ſaid unto you be circumſpect,</hi> i.e. be carefull to obſerve withall atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Audacia eſt de bo no divini praecepti diſputare, nec qula bonum eſt auſcultare debemus, ſed quia Deus praecepit. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. de poenit.</note> (Vatablus in H. C.) whatſoever I ſhall command you. There is reaſon enough in Gods will, and his meer command requires abſolute obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt ſhewes us a neceſſity of it, and tells us that <hi>whoſoever is unjuſt in the leaſt, is unjuſt alſo in much:</hi> and <hi>James</hi> ſaith, if he <hi>offend but in one point,</hi> and allow himſelfe in it, <hi>he is guilty of all,</hi> and he <hi>ſhall be the leaſt in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God;</hi> i. e. be of no account in Gods Church here,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.10. Jam. 2.10 Mat. 5.19.</note> nor have any part in heaven hereafter. So that you ſee that it is not enough to be <hi>willing in ſomething,</hi> but we muſt be <hi>willing in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:52020:66"/>
            <p n="3">3. What is done for God muſt be done <hi>equally.</hi> If you doe this dutie and neglect that duty, they both being commanded by the ſame wiſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God,<note place="margin">John 2.5.</note> there is no equality in it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it accepted. Therefore as <hi>Mary</hi> to the <hi>ſervants</hi> that waited on Chriſt, ſaid unto them, <hi>whatſoever he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſee that you do it:</hi> So ſay I to all, that who ſo will have a <hi>ſure character</hi> of a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> his obedience muſt be univerſall, whatſoever he commands we muſt endeavour to do it. <hi>Quicquid propter Deum fit aequaliter fit.</hi> You muſt have an equall <hi>reſpect to all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> Pſ. 119.6. You muſt (with David) fulfill all his will.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word is in the plurall number; all his wills.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
               </label> This then may ſerve to undeceive all <hi>halfe hearted</hi> Chriſtians, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into Gods <hi>Tabernacle</hi> here below, doubt not but they ſhall aſcend his <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mountaine</hi> hereafter; and why, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are willing to <hi>heare</hi> many <hi>truths,</hi> and willing to <hi>performe</hi> many <hi>duties.</hi> I tell thee if thou be not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:52020:66"/>to <hi>heare all,</hi> and <hi>doe all,</hi> thou wilt deceive thy ſelfe at laſt. Look upon <hi>Herod, Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> were they not Profeſſors, did they not <hi>heare</hi> much, and <hi>doe</hi> much, how was it then that they became ſuch ſad ſpectacles of Gods vengeance, that the one was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten up with <hi>wormes,</hi> and the other ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with ſudden <hi>death?</hi> I anſwer, though they were willing in <hi>many</hi> things, yet not in <hi>all</hi> things:<note place="margin">Act. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> will keep his <hi>Herodias,</hi> and <hi>Ananias</hi> will keep back part of the <hi>price,</hi> and by reſerving a part loſe all. Oh take it to heart all <hi>civill</hi> men and <hi>hypocrites,</hi> you both are but halfe Chiſtians, you anſwer Gods voice but as the <hi>Eccho</hi> doth anſwer the voice of a man, only in part not in whole, but God will not be ſo anſwered, he will have all or none. Do not ſay with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman, The Lord be mercifull unto me when I goe into the houſe of Rimmon:</hi> The Lord be mercifull unto me if I <hi>ſweare raſhly, commit Adultery, oppreſſe my Brother.,</hi> or act this or that <hi>wicked neſſe.</hi> Know God will have no reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he will not have thee <hi>ſwallow a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:52020:67"/>Camell,</hi> nor yet a <hi>gnat.</hi> As he will have thee to tremble at <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>bloud.</hi> ſo will he have thee to feare <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>troth:</hi> As to abhorre <hi>Adulterie,</hi> ſo to hate <hi>Daliance.</hi> As to loath the ſhedding of <hi>bloud,</hi> ſo to ſhun the taking away of any part of thy Brothers <hi>livelihood.</hi> One ſpeaking of <hi>conſcience</hi> tells us it is a <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of precious oyntment, that muſt not be corrupted with the leaſt Fly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sam: Ward</note> Soe I ſay, take heed of any thing that may offend God an <hi>conſcience,</hi> and let it be thy care with <hi>Zachariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth to walke in the commandements of God without reproofe,</hi> Luk. 1.6. ſo ſhalt thou diſcover the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of thy <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> with <hi>Paul,</hi> when thou art not only <hi>willing,</hi> but <hi>willing in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Character of a <hi>good conſcience</hi> is conſtancy in wel-doing: Paul doth not ſay that he is willing to make a ſtep or two in holineſſe, and then leave off: no he is reſolved to <hi>walke</hi> on, to make it his conſtant practice, yea to <hi>live</hi> alwaies in and with a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> A little child may go a ſtep or two before he fall, yea a very drunkard may ſeeme togoe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:52020:67"/>ſteddy at firſt, and yet if you obſerve him, he will at laſt reele and tumble, this is no argument of <hi>ſtrength</hi> or <hi>ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe.</hi> Even ſo if men ſhall do good duties for a fitt once or twice &amp;c. and give over and fall off, this is no ſigne of a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> as there muſt be an univerſality, <hi>in all things,</hi> ſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, <hi>alwaies:</hi> as in Paul Act. 23.1. &amp; 24.16. <hi>He lived in all good conſcience</hi> unto the laſt; he kept his conſcience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive alwaies, he walked without tripping, without ſtumbling, ever the ſame in all <hi>actions</hi> and in all <hi>conditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
               </label> Conſider this you <hi>hypocrites</hi> and <hi>time-ſervers</hi> who are conſtant in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in inconſtancy, now for God, and then for <hi>Baal;</hi> this day <hi>holy,</hi> to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>prophane;</hi> to day you will make a ſtep or two towards <hi>heaven,</hi> to morrow as many &amp; more large ſtrides to <hi>hell. Will the hypocrite pray alwaies?</hi> will he be obedient <hi>in all things?</hi> ſurely noe: he is a ſtranger to univerſall obedience, a ſtranger to conſtant obedience, and ſo a ſtranger to a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> Oh therefore as thou deſireſt a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:52020:68"/>
               <hi>good conſcience,</hi> ſo deſire of God a right way to walk in, begge of him to <hi>teach</hi> thee his <hi>way,</hi> i. e. ſuch a courſe of life as might be pleaſing unto him, and to <hi>lead thee in a plaine path,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 27.11.</note> that thou mayeſt walk in it without tripping and ſtumbling. This way of God in which thou art to walke in, it is the way of Gods ſtatutes, if therefore thou once get into this way, take heed of going out of it, let that reſolution be in thee which was in <hi>David, Teach me O Lord the way of thy ſtatutes and I will keep it unto the end, Pſ.</hi> 119.33. Reſolve to be conſtant without <hi>tripping</hi> or <hi>turning either to the right hand or to the left:</hi> ſo ſhalt thou be aſſured that thy <hi>conſcience</hi> is <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Character of a <hi>good conſcience</hi> is ſincerity, the word in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and our Tranſlators read it, <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly,</hi> the word is very comprehenſive and containes within it as much as any, or all other Adverbs in Scripture, namely <hi>worthily, decently, accurately, circumſpectly, lively, famouſly,</hi> and <hi>praiſeworthy.</hi> It notes unto us the luſtre
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:52020:68"/>of an action, and tells us that a <hi>good conſcience</hi> ſtands not ſo much in <hi>verbs,</hi> as in <hi>adverbs;</hi> not ſo much in <hi>doing,</hi> as in <hi>Welldoing;</hi> if a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> he rules <hi>diligently;</hi> if a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> he preacheth <hi>willingly;</hi> if a <hi>hearer,</hi> he heareth <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively;</hi> if a <hi>ſupplicant,</hi> he prayeth <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently;</hi> yea whatſoever he does in the worſhip of his God he doth it <hi>faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Rom. 12.8. Phil. 2.20.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
               </label> Conſider this you carnall men and women, who content your ſelves with the bare doing of a duty, without reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the manner of doing. If you <hi>eare the word, read, pray,</hi> and <hi>practiſe ſome good duty of piety or charity,</hi> you thinke you have done all, and all well: Oh remember that if it be not done <hi>honeſtly,</hi> (that is) <hi>ſyncerely,</hi> in obedience to God both for <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>end,</hi> your <hi>conſcience</hi> is not <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me therefore adviſe you in every duty that you do performe, obſerve an honourable <hi>decorum,</hi> I ſpeake to <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, bond</hi> and <hi>free, male</hi> and <hi>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> of what ranke and condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: reſt not ſatisfied in your doing of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:52020:69"/>any duty, except it be done <hi>honeſtly, faithfully,</hi> and <hi>praiſe-worthily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> be you in the <hi>higheſt</hi> place of <hi>Judicature,</hi> or in the <hi>loweſt</hi> place of <hi>office:</hi> minde your <hi>Oathes,</hi> your places your <hi>truſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 48.10.</note> doe not Gods work <hi>negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,</hi> leaſt a <hi>woe</hi> befall you, and Gods <hi>curſe</hi> ſeize upon you, but have reſpect unto your owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> and unto the <hi>conſciences</hi> of others, that your owne may be preſerved: and the <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> of others rectified.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Miniſters,</hi> I muſt ſpeak to you as the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> were to ſpeak to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus, Take heed to the Miniſtry which you have received,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gol. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>that you fulfill it,</hi> ſee you doe your <hi>whole worke</hi> in delivering the <hi>whole truth,</hi> and in being an <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all holineſſe unto your flock, preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, do the worke of an Evangeliſt</hi> ſo fully and <hi>honeſtly,</hi> that you may appeare to be men <hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God</hi> to preach the Goſpell: and that your <hi>preaching</hi> hath not been to <hi>pleaſe men</hi> but <hi>God which tryeth the heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.4.</note> Thus ſhall you evidence a <hi>good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> when you ſeek to ſatisfy your <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:52020:69"/>in every duty of your calling.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Governours of Families,</hi> think it not enough that you have ſo many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your command, and that you can ſay <hi>to this ſervant goe, and he goeth,</hi> and <hi>unto that ſervant come and he cometh;</hi> ſee well unto it that your <hi>commands</hi> and <hi>countermands</hi> be all honeſt, doe that which is juſt &amp; equall unto them. Doe you firſt with <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſerve God <hi>your ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 24.</note> and then reſolve that <hi>your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> ſhall doe the like. If any be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſee with <hi>Abraham</hi> that you teach them. If any be unteachable, untracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſee with <hi>David</hi> you exclude them, let them not abide in your houſe, ſo ſhall your houſes be <hi>Bethels, houſes of God,</hi> and your ſelves <hi>men of God,</hi> and men of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Private perſons,</hi> be you not <hi>Chams</hi> but <hi>Jonathans,</hi> Be you carefull of your owne <hi>conſciences,</hi> &amp; then be carefull of the <hi>conſciences</hi> of your Brethren, <hi>hate not</hi> your brethren <hi>in your hearts, but reprove them plainely, &amp; ſuffer not ſin to reſt upon them,</hi> Lev. 19 17. Yea thou muſt <hi>love thy neighbour as they ſelfe</hi> v. 18. there muſt be a conformity in <hi>quality,</hi> though
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:52020:70"/>not a correſpondence of <hi>equality,</hi> thy love to thy brother and to thy ſelfe muſt be like in kind for <hi>ſincerity</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>deceit,</hi> and for <hi>efficacy</hi> without <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> If thou do thus <hi>love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 3.18.</note> thou loveſt thy God, and thou loveſt a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly <hi>to every one</hi> of what <hi>ſex</hi> or <hi>condition</hi> ſoever, whether <hi>rich</hi> or <hi>poor,</hi> let <hi>conſcience</hi> be your Totum, all that thou haſt to do is to look well to <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Art thou <hi>rich,</hi> let <hi>conſcience</hi> be thy <hi>bagg:</hi> if <hi>poor,</hi> let <hi>conſcience</hi> by thy <hi>cruſe,</hi> if a <hi>wife,</hi> let <hi>conſcience</hi> be thy <hi>glaſſe;</hi> if a <hi>wayd,</hi> let <hi>conſcience</hi> be thy <hi>attire:</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou art, ſubmit to <hi>conſcience,</hi> let that command thee, be <hi>ruled</hi> by it, and it will not <hi>wrong</hi> thee, be <hi>familiar</hi> with it, and it will never <hi>deceive</hi> thee.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what is to be done in the exerciſe of a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> 1. A willingneſſe to <hi>pleaſe</hi> God. 2. To pleaſe him <hi>in all things.</hi> 3. To pleaſe him <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies.</hi> and 4. to do all this <hi>truly, ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>honeſtly.</hi> Thus to doe is the very life and ſoule of all practicall piety.</p>
            <p>As thou loveſt thy ſoule, miſſe not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:52020:70"/>one of theſe <hi>charecters,</hi> they are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny golden linkes faſtened by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he that hath one of them, hath all, and if but one be wanting, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe the reſt are miſſing. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a neceſſity of them all, for as in a <hi>ſound body</hi> there muſt be a due mixture and compoſition of all the 4 <hi>elements</hi> and Humors: ſo in a <hi>ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> there muſt be a due compoſition of all theſe 4 <hi>characters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Uſe to ſuch as <hi>have, hold,</hi> &amp; thus <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> to proclaime Gods bounty, that they with others may mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify God, we read that the 4 <hi>Lepers in Samaria,</hi> having found a ſudden &amp; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py change from <hi>penury to plenty;</hi> they blamed themſelves for being ſilent and not divulging this great mercy:<note place="margin">2 King. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>We doe not well</hi> (ſay they) <hi>this day is a day of good tydings, and we hold our peace.</hi> So ſhall I ſay unto you that have found this great and gracious change in your ſelves, that your evill <hi>conſcience</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> You ſhall not do well to be ſilent, but with <hi>David,</hi> it is your part and duty ſpeedily to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:52020:71"/>unto others. <hi>Come unto me all you that feare God. and I will tell you what God hath done for my ſoule.</hi> Pſ. 66.18. I ſay againe its your duty and you are very faulty if you doe it not.</p>
            <p>Acknowledge your <hi>miſery by nature,</hi> and likewiſe your <hi>happineſſe by Grace;</hi> ſay with all humility &amp; thankfulneſſe, I was by <hi>nature</hi> as vile as the worſt, as deeply guilty in <hi>Adams</hi> ſin as any; as fouly polluted with <hi>Originall</hi> ſin as the verieſt Reprobate, and had in me the <hi>ſeed of all ſin,</hi> apt to be drawne unto the fouleſt and groſſeſt tranſgreſſions, and to <hi>run to the ſame exceſſe of riot with the worſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">tit. 1.15.</note> yea my very <hi>ſoule and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was defiled.</hi> But bleſſed by my good God that hath ſtriken <hi>Covenant</hi> with me in my bleſſed Saviour Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">Ezek. 11.19.</note> &amp; hath put into me a <hi>new Spirit,</hi> given me a <hi>heart of fleſh,</hi> and hath changed this <hi>defiled conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> into a <hi>pure conſcience,</hi> a <hi>conſcience</hi> both purified and pacified by the bloud and ſpirit of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Col. 1.20.</note> My greateſt <hi>foe</hi> is now become my greateſt <hi>friend,</hi> a moſt <hi>true</hi> friend, that will not flatter me, but deale plainly with me,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:52020:71"/>a moſt <hi>ſweet</hi> freind that will comfort me in the ſaddeſt and darkeſt times and ſeaſons, yea a friend that will make me to <hi>laugh</hi> under the <hi>whip. Sing</hi> when my <hi>feet</hi> are <hi>in the ſtocks</hi> and <hi>rejoyce when I fall into many Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> In a word, a moſt <hi>conſtant</hi> friend, that <hi>will never leave me nor forſake me</hi> neither in this life nor in the life to come. <hi>Death</hi> may part <hi>Naomi</hi> and <hi>Ruth. David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> but <hi>death</hi> ſhall never parte <hi>thee</hi> and thy <hi>conſcience,</hi> ſhe will be with the in <hi>reproach and povertie,</hi> in <hi>ſickneſſe and diſtreſſe,</hi> in <hi>priſon and reſtraint,</hi> in <hi>lyfe,</hi> in <hi>death,</hi> in <hi>Judgment,</hi> and before Gods <hi>Tribunall.</hi> Oh therefore relate thy happie and bleſſed change unto others that ſo thou, and they may unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly prayſe God: Soe ſhall <hi>thy God</hi> be <hi>magnified</hi> and thine owne <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart</hi> reallie and faithfull <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Uſe; to ſuch as have a <hi>good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> to be ſuch a <hi>friend</hi> unto them, that they would be very Carefull, to deale <hi>friendly</hi> with this friend, It is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:52020:72"/>
               <hi>Solomons</hi> Adviſe; Prov. 18.24. That <hi>he that hath friends muſt deale friendly:</hi> and that <hi>there is a friend that ſticketh cloſer then a Brother.</hi> Now <hi>conſcience</hi> is this <hi>cloſe friend,</hi> let Father, Mother, Husband, Wife, Child, and Neigbour, all leave thee, This friend <hi>will never leave thee nor forſake thee,</hi> as I told thee formerly; Oh therefore deale <hi>friendly</hi> with thy <hi>Conſcience,</hi> give not the leaſt offence unto her, but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhe is very tender and will be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the leaſt wrong or injury done unto her: The <hi>Injurie of a friend</hi> doth ſtick cloſer then the <hi>wrong of an Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. David</hi> could ſay, <hi>had it been an Enimie,</hi> that had done me this wrong, I <hi>could have borne it, but it was thou my friend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 41.9.</note> 
               <hi>yea my familiar friend, we tooke ſweet counſell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 55.13.</note> Take heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do neither <hi>diſuſe conſcience,</hi> nor <hi>miſuſe conſcience</hi> (1) I ſay doe not <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe conſciene</hi> by eſtraunging thy ſelfe from her and refuſing her Adviſe and counſell. 2 Doe not <hi>miſuſe her</hi> (1) Some by making her a <hi>cloak</hi> for any errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>opinion</hi> or ſinfull <hi>practice</hi> as too to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:52020:72"/>many doe in theſe our daies, who dare to ſet Gods <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Supſcription</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne baſe <hi>coine,</hi> Are there not many amongſt us who impudently, and blaſphemouſly affirme, that their <hi>Miſſion, Meſſage, Doctrine, and Spirit</hi> are all of God. They will tell you, <hi>they are ſent of God,</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> they teach is the mind and <hi>will of God The Spirit</hi> by which they teach,<note place="margin">Iſ. 8.20.</note> it is the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> But come you to the <hi>law</hi> and to the <hi>teſtimonie,</hi> conſult the word of God and you ſhall find, <hi>there is no light in them.</hi> They are very <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> of heaven, abuſing his Image and Superſcription, read but the 23 of Jer. and 13 of Ezek. and you ſhall find that notwithſtanding their great Braggs, they are but groſſe impoſtours and ſeducers. God tels them <hi>He never ſent them, never ſpake unto them,</hi> &amp; calls them <hi>Dreamers</hi> whoſe <hi>Doctrine</hi> is but <hi>chaffe,</hi> and <hi>their Spirit, is not Gods Spirit,</hi> but their own proud, lying, and deluding ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others make <hi>conſcience</hi> a Cloak, for ungodly practices, that they may
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:52020:73"/>the more cloſſely oppreſſe, defraud and injure others, to the ſatisfying of their ambitious luſts and Covetous deſires, ſuch were the <hi>Scribs</hi> &amp; <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> of old, of whom our <hi>Saviour</hi> gives us a Caveat, that wee <hi>beware of</hi> them and then deſcribes them, that people might the better know them. They are men ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> that carrie a great ſhew of Pyetie and holineſſe, <hi>they pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23.14.</note> yea <hi>make long prayers</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme other godlie exerciſes,<note place="margin">Luk. 20.46.</note> and all this they doe <hi>not ſyncerely</hi> but <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critically, that they may</hi> the more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>devoure widdowes houſes,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their eſtates, who entertaine them: and doubtles many ſuch there are amongſt us at this time, who have very faire <hi>pretences</hi> for moſt <hi>foule practices;</hi> as <hi>Jezabel</hi> had, who was never more zealous in <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>faſting</hi> then when ſhe intended to to take away the life and livelihood of innocent <hi>Naboth;</hi> now what are theſe but great abuſers of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To theſe I may Adde a third ſort who having abuſed <hi>conſcience;</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:52020:73"/>by ſome ungodly Art of <hi>whordome, drunkenneſſe, blaſphemy</hi> or the like, will call for mercy and ſo be friends. It is reported of <hi>Lewes the eleventh</hi> King of France, that he wore in his Hat a Crucifix, and when at any time he had blaſphemed God or acted any wickedneſſe; <hi>He</hi> would preſently take downe his Crucifix and Kiſſe it, and then he had thought he had made ſatisfaction for all wrongs; even ſo is it amongſt us, There are many when they have done any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>conſcience,</hi> thinke it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Kiſſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> and cry <hi>God have mercy</hi> and all is well: but let me tell ſuch, they are <hi>enimies to conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and let them be aſſured that at laſt they will find Conſcience an <hi>enimie to them,</hi> yea their <hi>greateſt eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie:</hi> Not only a witneſſe, But their Judge and Tormentor.</p>
            <p>Uſe of Exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> unto all to be very carefull how they deale with <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> not to dare to injure it in the leaſt degree, <hi>conſcience</hi> I muſt tell you is verie tender, ſoone ſenſible of the leaſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:52020:74"/>wrong: if therefore you will hold friendſhip with her you muſt reſolve to be tender alſo, and that with an holy tenderneſſe, I ſay an holy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and the rather becauſe there is too much tenderneſſe in the world which is very hatefull unto a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Some are very ready for the <hi>practice</hi> of ſin,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Unholy Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> but they are ſo tender, as they cannot endure the leaſt touch of <hi>reproofe</hi> for ſin, They are like thoſe whole bodies being full of <hi>boyles</hi> and <hi>botches</hi> cry out unto ſuch as come neer them: Oh do not touch me and all becauſe of the ſoares and and the ulcers they beare about them.</p>
            <p>Thus is it which many a wicked man and woman who having many <hi>ulcers of ſin</hi> running upon them will not indure their Chriſtian <hi>friends</hi> nor yet their faithful <hi>miniſters</hi> and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers but cry out, like thoſe in <hi>Iſaiah, who ſaid to the ſeers ſee not, &amp; to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prepheſie not unto us right things, but ſpeak ſmooth things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 30.10.</note> 
               <hi>propheſy deceit,</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:52020:74"/>They cannot indure to heare the <hi>truth of God, but a lie,</hi> not to have Gods Judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts threatned, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be <hi>ſlattered,</hi> though it turne unto their owne <hi>ruine:</hi> Such tender perſons were <hi>Amaziah</hi> the prince,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 25.16.</note> and <hi>Amaziah</hi> the prieſt. The firſt was reproved by the prophet of the Covenant: for <hi>ſetting up of falſe Gods:</hi> but the King tells the <hi>Prophet</hi> that he ſhould hold his <hi>peace, leaſt he were ſmitten,</hi> he was ſo tender he could not beare it. The like temper we find in <hi>Amaziah</hi> the prieſt when <hi>Amos</hi> propheſied the <hi>rejection of Iſrael and the deſtruction of Jeroboams houſe by the ſword,</hi> preſentlie. <hi>Amaziah</hi> goes to incenſe the <hi>King</hi> againſt <hi>Amos,</hi> and tells him that the <hi>land was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare his words,</hi> and bids him ſlee away and not to come againe unto <hi>Bethel,</hi> for it was the <hi>Kings chappell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 7.10.</note> a place that he had Conſecrated to the <hi>worſhip of the Calves,</hi> &amp; therefore not ſafe nor fitting for <hi>Amos</hi> to propheſie againſt him in that place.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:52020:75"/>
            <p n="2">2. Some are naturally tender, of ſuch a ſoft and tender Temper, that they readily yeeld unto any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of man, though countermaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by god. Thus was it with <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im. Hoſ.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Ephraim is broken in Judgment:</hi> becauſe <hi>he willingly walked after the Commandement,</hi> what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, the wicked comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of their Idolatrous Kings and princes, therefore the Lord Threatens them that he would be to <hi>Ephraim as a Moth, &amp; to the houſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah rottenneſſe.</hi> i.e. <hi>He</hi> would conſume them by little and little as a <hi>Moth</hi> doth a <hi>garment,</hi> or as a <hi>worme</hi> doth a peice of <hi>Timber,</hi> and ſurely this may be ſaid to be our caſe: our preferring <hi>mans mandates</hi> before <hi>Gods Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands,</hi> hath <hi>broken us</hi> of this land <hi>in peices,</hi> and if God be unto us as he was to <hi>Ephraim</hi> a <hi>Moth</hi> and a <hi>worme</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually to ruine us, it is but His Juſtice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Others there are which are ſcrupelouſly tender, They will ſtick at ſtrawes and leap over blocks,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:52020:75"/>make that a ſin which God never made a ſin, and ſtirr moſt in that, in which God is ſilent, Thus the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſcruple their going into the <hi>Praetorium,</hi> the houſe of an <hi>Heathen</hi> man, leaſt they ſhould be <hi>ceromoniallie</hi> defiled and ſoe held from the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> but yet made no matter of de filing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>morally</hi> with the guilt of <hi>innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud:</hi> againe, they are troubled in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>price of bloud</hi> into their holy <hi>Corbam,</hi> but not troubled to give a <hi>price to ſhed innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud. How carefull</hi> are they in <hi>waſhing of hands, of cups, pots, and platters,</hi> how <hi>careleſſe</hi> in <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> and inſides from ſin. One ſaith well: ſuch as theſe, <hi>they can dance amongſt thornes and yet know not how to walke upon even ground; Herod</hi> had too much of this render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when he had paſſed his word &amp; given his oath to grant his wicked <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodias</hi> her unreaſonable requeſt, which was, to have <hi>John Baptiſt head in a char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> Note the tenderneſſe of this man, he may not breake his <hi>Oath,</hi> and therefore concludes that to go back
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:52020:76"/>from his word, would be <hi>perjurie:</hi> but to go on, though it were to ſhed the bloud of an <hi>innocent,</hi> this he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>pietie.</hi> Many ſuch we have amonſt us who doe more ſcruple an egg then an Oath, and like <hi>Eſops</hi> dogg doe ſo greedily catch at <hi>ſhadowes,</hi> that they looſe the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> therefore I would ſuch would be more wiſe, following the Advice of <hi>Paul,</hi> who in unneceſſarie and vaine ſcruples will have us to <hi>asks no Queſtion for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.25.</note> Beware of all ſuch evill and ſinfull tenderneſſe, as enimies to a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> and labour for ſuch a tenderneſſe as is holy and faultleſſe which will make you watchfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every ſin, that may any waies moleſt or diſquiet <hi>conſcience,</hi> thus far of an <hi>unholy tenderneſſe,</hi> which cannot ſtand with a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> Now followes <hi>an holy tenderneſſe</hi> which ſuits well with <hi>conſcience</hi> and keeps us and our <hi>conſciences</hi> at peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holy tenderneſſe</hi> is ſuch a tenderneſſe as is wrought in us by the holy ſpirit of God,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Holy Tenderneſſe. Sheff.</note> whereby we are made very
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:52020:76"/>watchfull againſt whatſoever may mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt or diſquet <hi>conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a tenderneſſe we find in <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who when his <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> tempted him to <hi>lye with her,</hi> he preſently refuſed it, and ſaid unto her, <hi>behold my Maſter wotteth not what is in the houſe with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>and he hath committed all to my hand, and there is none greater in his houſe then I, neither hath he kept any thing from me but thee, becauſe thou art his wife, how then can I doe this great wickedneſſe and ſinagainſt God.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid unto her, your deſire is very wicked and I may not yeild unto it, I may not act the leaſt ſin againſt God; how then may I commit ſo great a wickedneſſe as to <hi>defile</hi> my <hi>Maſters bed?</hi> is it not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, a complicated ſin that contains many evills within it. In ſo doing, 1. I ſhould be a <hi>Theefe</hi> in ſtealing from him the beſt jewell in his houſe, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his wife. 2. Moſt injurious in mixing a <hi>baſtard brood</hi> with his <hi>legitimate chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> 3. I ſhould be ſacrilegious in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my body which is the <hi>temple of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and to turne it to <hi>carnall pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:52020:77"/>4. I ſhould be moſt <hi>ungracious</hi> toward my God and moſt <hi>ingratefull</hi> to my kind Maſter. The like we find in <hi>Job,</hi> a man very fearefull to offend <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> he was a <hi>Nonſuch</hi> by Gods owne teſtimony,<note place="margin">Job. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>not any one like him upon the earth,</hi> ſoe <hi>perfect,</hi> ſoe <hi>upright, fearing God and eſchewing evill.</hi> He was one that reſolved not to give <hi>conſcience</hi> the leaſt offence, and that it ſhould <hi>not reproach him all his dayes.</hi> Though men did reproach him as <hi>Eliphas, Bildad, Zophar,</hi> who charged him with <hi>hypos criſy,</hi> yet his <hi>conſcience</hi> which was more privy to his waies, and could teſtify more truly,<note place="margin">Job. 27.6.</note> that ſhould not <hi>reproach him,</hi> ſo tender was he.</p>
            <p>Such muſt be our <hi>tenderneſſe;</hi> the like was that in <hi>Ioſeph, Job,</hi> and others: and that we may not be deceived, know how it ſhewes it ſelfe to God, to others, and to our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To God,</hi> he that hath an holy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe in him will ſtand for God in what ſhall make for his <hi>truth, honour,</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of his name, if he ſee any thing unto which God is intitled or
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:52020:77"/>hath intereſt in, ſuch a one will not ſee his God wronged in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, but he will ſtand upon an <hi>hoof</hi> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; upon an <hi>iota</hi> or <hi>title</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he, will manifeſt his tenderneſſe in all things. As 1. to his precepts. 2.<note place="margin">Exod. 10.26.</note> To his Threats. 3. His Judgments. 4. His Mercies. Of theſe in their order:<note place="margin">Math. 5.18</note> and Firſt of the firſt, namely, Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.<note place="margin">Cauti eſto te. Vatab. in h. l.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He that hath this holy tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in him will readily yeild unto Gods <hi>precepts,</hi> whatſoever he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands he will do it <hi>circumſpectly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia bona non ſolúm attendit quid prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiat De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſed quid velit, quae ſit vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas Dei bona, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neplacens et perfect. Bern. de virâ ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ ad fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres de monte D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i p. 10 20.</note> i. e. warily and with attention, Exod. 23.13. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>faithfull in all his houſe,</hi> i. e. the Church of God in his time, and wherein God was pleaſed to dwell; <hi>Moſes</hi> was in all things very exact to obey Gods <hi>precepts:</hi> Againe we find <hi>Joſias</hi> very tender in the <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of whatſoever the Lord <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> ſoe that there was never a King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after him that ſo <hi>turned unto the Lord with all his heart according to the law of Moſes.</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> the firſt
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:52020:78"/>
               <hi>walked before God with an upright heart;</hi> the latter ſhewed himſelfe a moſt <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> man againſt <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſinners.</hi> How tender was he for the honour of his God, in the <hi>obſervation</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> in the <hi>maintenance</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and howſoever againſt the <hi>prophaners of the Sabbath,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>oppreſſed</hi> their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by <hi>uſury.</hi> Read the 5th. of Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, and the 13th. of Nehemiah.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He that hath this holy tenderneſſe, will quickly yeild, melt, and break under any <hi>threat</hi> of Gods word or ſence of Gods diſpleaſure. If <hi>Joſias</hi> doe but heare the <hi>book read,</hi> in which the threats and menaces of Gods wrath are recorded; he preſently melts and thaws, he <hi>rents his cloathes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 22 19.</note> 
               <hi>mournes and weeps, ſhall the Lyon roare, and the Beaſts not tremble? or a trumpet ſound, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not feare?</hi> Soe if God roare againſt a Nation and people, ſhall they not quake?<note place="margin">Jer. 36.24.</note> Let hard <hi>hearted Jehoiakim</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine obſtinate, yet <hi>good Ioſiah</hi> will <hi>rent his cloathes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This holy tenderneſſe will make a man to mourne under Gos <hi>judgments:</hi>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:52020:78"/>He that melts under Gos <hi>threats,</hi> will ſurely cry out under his <hi>judgments: He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> if hee feele <hi>gods rod</hi> upon him,<note place="margin">Jſ. 38.14.</note> he will <hi>mourne like a Dove, and chatter like a Crane.</hi> Let God take <hi>Job</hi> by the <hi>neck anà ſhake him,</hi> and cauſe his <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to compaſſe him about,</hi> i. e. many afflictions and troubles, it will make him to ſow <hi>ſackcloth upon his ſkin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 16.12 15.</note> 
               <hi>and defile his horne in the duſt,</hi> yea <hi>it will make his face foule with weeping, and cauſe the ſhaddow of death upon his eyelids,</hi> i. e. to wax dimme and darke as if they were dying, and puts upon him ſuch a ſtamp of true ſorrow, as it makes him to cry out, <hi>I abhorre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes.</hi> But on the contrary it is neither <hi>threat,</hi> nor <hi>judgment,</hi> that workes upon the <hi>uncircumciſed heart,</hi> he <hi>refuſeth the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of his iniquity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 36.23</note> 
               <hi>and cryeth not when the Lord binds him,</hi> i. e. afflicteth him: but the more God afflicts, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he growes, and doth <hi>revolt more and more.</hi> Iſ. 1.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This holy tenderneſſe makes him humble under Gods <hi>mercies.</hi> The more mercifull that God is to him, the more
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:52020:79"/>tender he is for God, he <hi>feareth God and his goodneſſe.</hi> As Ice contracted with cold diſſolves of it ſelfe under the warme raies and beames of the Sun, ſo doth his Soule melt and thaw under the ſenſe of Gods favour,<note place="margin">Ezra 9.14</note> like thoſe in <hi>Ezra</hi> who having received a great <hi>deliverance</hi> from thier <hi>enimies,</hi> ſaid one to another, ſeeing our God hath been ſo gracious, <hi>ſhall wee againe breake his commandes ments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 7.47.</note> Thus in <hi>Mary Magdaline,</hi> we read how ſhe <hi>ſtood behind Chriſt and wept,</hi> that ſhe to wept and mourned for her ſins, as that ſhe waſht Chriſts <hi>feet with her teares, and wiped them with the haire of her head, yea kiſſed his feet, and anointed them with oyntment:</hi> and why ſo? how comes this tenderneſſe upon her? what ſhould cauſe it? truly, Chriſt his great mercy unto her, in pardoning her great and many ſins; this is the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony which Chriſt gives of her, <hi>ſhe loved much, becauſe much was forgiven her.</hi> So that you ſee how holy tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will yeild unto Gods mercies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This holy tenderneſſe will ſhew it ſelfe to <hi>others;</hi> it will make a man ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:52020:79"/>carefull not to offend others, it will <hi>give no offence to Jew nor Gentile, nor to the Church of God,</hi> i. e. no occaſion of offence of ſcandall unto <hi>Jew</hi> or Pagan or Chriſtian, neither within, nor yet without the Church.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.32.</note> As it was Pauls <hi>precept,</hi> ſo likewiſe his <hi>practice;</hi> who is <hi>offended</hi> (at leaſt through my default) <hi>and I bvrne not,</hi> i. e.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.29.</note> burne with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and holy indignation and ardent zeale for the glory of God, and falvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that are ſcandalized? <hi>Paul</hi> was a man alwaies for peace, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it upon others: <hi>As much as in you lyeth have peace with all men,</hi> but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with the godly; as for himſelfe his <hi>conſcience</hi> was ſo tender, that he would neither ſay nor doe any thing, that might give <hi>offence to weake Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, if eating of fleſh would offend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>he reſolves to eat no fleſh while the world ſtandeth.</hi> So it is with all ſuch as are truly tender, if their <hi>meat, drink, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell,</hi> if their <hi>haire, carriage, company,</hi> or any other thing, ſhall give an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence unto their <hi>Brethren,</hi> they reſolve with <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>cate no more fleſh, drinke</hi> no
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:52020:80"/>more <hi>wine, weare</hi> no more long <hi>haire,</hi> keep no more ſuch <hi>company,</hi> leave off all rather then give any offence or be a <hi>ſtumbling block</hi> unto their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>And as this tenderneſſe appeares to all, ſoe eſpecially unto ſuch as ſtand in any neer relation unto them, as wife or child, and how <hi>tender</hi> was <hi>Joſeph</hi> of his <hi>wives</hi> reputation and ſalvation, when ſhe was with Child, and he knew not how it ſhould be ſoe, and fearing the ſcandall that might come upon ſo gracious a woman, and loath ſhe ſhould be made a publick example,<note place="margin">Math. 1.19.</note> his <hi>reſolution was to put her away privily,</hi> to leave her to the diſpoſing of her friends and not to conſummate the Marriage. The like tenderneſſe towards <hi>Children</hi> we find in <hi>Job,</hi> he fearing leaſt in their <hi>feaſting</hi> they had gone beyond their bounds,<note place="margin">Job 1.5.</note> and ſoe <hi>diſhonoured God.</hi> He of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd a <hi>burnt-offering for them unto God every morning.</hi> i. e. an offering of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. which declared his religion toward God and care of his children. So <hi>Auſtin</hi> reports of his Mother <hi>Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:52020:80"/>that ſhe was ſo tender of the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her <hi>children,</hi> that if ſhe heard that any one of them had <hi>diſhonoured</hi> God, it wrought ſuch an impreſſion of griefe upon her ſoule, that it pained her as much as the new bearing of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other child. Thus you ſee how an holy tenderneſſe will ſhew it ſelfe to others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How an holy Tenderneſſe appears to our <hi>ſelves.</hi> he that is tender indeed will not, diſpleaſe his owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> he reſolves with David to ſly all ſin and ſinners: <hi>I abhorre</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>every evill way, and I will not endure a wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> ſuch <hi>perſons</hi> and ſuch <hi>practices</hi> are very hatefull unto him; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not brook ſin, in any degree, <hi>great</hi> ſins, <hi>little</hi> ſins, <hi>apparent</hi> ſins, or ſins in appearance, he declines them all, he conſiders that remarkable ſpeech of our <hi>Saviours,</hi> Luk. 16.15. <hi>That which is highly eſteemed amongſt men, is an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in the ſight of God.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dares not alwaies to adventure upon that which hath appearance of good, but brings it to the touch,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>tries all things, and ſo holds faſt</hi> (not what
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:52020:81"/>ſeems good,) but <hi>What is good.</hi> laſtly the render <hi>conſcience</hi> will take heed of what he knowes to be lawfull, he dares not to do all that he <hi>may</hi> doe, leaſt he ſhould do what he <hi>ought not to doe.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider you that are <hi>Gamſters, merry come panions, faſhion-mongers.</hi> and all <hi>fleſh-pleaſers,</hi> which are lovers of pleaſure, more then lovers of God. I know you will ſtand upon your <hi>juſtification,</hi> and plead ſtrongly for your <hi>dicing, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, carding,</hi> your <hi>long haire,</hi> your <hi>fantaſticall faſhions,</hi> and <hi>pot companions,</hi> though there be enough recorded in Gods book againſt them in all of theſe. Me thinks I heare you ſay there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>great Schollers</hi> will maintaine the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> and that it is <hi>condemned</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a company of <hi>ſtrict lacea Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> and men of meane parts and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Give me leave to ſpeak the <hi>words of truth</hi> and <hi>ſoberneſſe:</hi> you ſay <hi>cards, dice, drinking,</hi> and <hi>merry company</hi> are things lawfull;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.12.</note> but anſwer me, 1. are they <hi>expedient.</hi> 2. Doe they <hi>edify</hi> you. 3. Are they not <hi>brought under the power</hi> of theſe things, theſe practices. Alas
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:52020:81"/>who ſees not ſuch as thus ſeek to <hi>pleaſe</hi> the fleſh that they do <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> God, their merry company makes them to diſtaſt the ſociety of Saints; their <hi>dicing</hi> and <hi>drinking</hi> makes them to loath the <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>reading</hi> of Gods word; yea <hi>Bible</hi> and the pack of <hi>Cards</hi> are like the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Dagon,</hi> they will not <hi>ſtand together.</hi> Let me therefore adviſe you not to be too preſumptuous upon the lawfulneſſe of theſe, but conſider ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency and edification, that all be done ſoe that God may have glory, and your ſelves may be edified more and more in Chriſt. If you look not to this, that which is lawfull in it ſelfe will be found unlawfull in you. You will ſoon be brought <hi>under their power</hi> &amp; be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated by what ſhould be your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore what on ſaith and that moſt truly, <hi>licitis perimus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the Whole world is undone by lawfull things.</hi> i. e. lawfull things abuſed or miſeſteemed. Was it not ſo with the <hi>old world,</hi> when our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpeaketh of the deſtruction of the <hi>old world by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:52020:82"/>what doth our <hi>Saviour</hi> charge u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them as deſerving this great and generall judgement? he mentions only things that were both lawfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: <hi>They did eate, hey dranke, they bought and ſold, they built and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they married and were given in marriage:</hi> See you any unlawfulneſſe in any of theſe? notwithſtanding the giving themſelves up to theſe things,<note place="margin">Luk. 17.27.</note> ſuffering ſuch practices to call them off from God. God was highly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and themſelves fearfully periſhed. Oh therefore doe not preſume upon the lawfulneſſe of ſuch things, but if you have this holy tenderneſſe in thee, examine all circumſtances leaſt God be offended, and thy <hi>conſcience</hi> ſo woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as that thou canſt find no peace within, but in thy apprehenſion a very reprobate.</p>
            <p>One word more by way of <hi>comfort</hi> unto you that are thus tender,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Uſe of Comfort.</note> poſſible it is that though you deſire tenderneſſe and to hold a firme peace with <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> yet your <hi>conſcience</hi> may frowne upon you, and ſo you conclude againſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:52020:82"/>your ſelfe that God is angry with you, according to that of the Apoſtle, 1. Joh 3.21. <hi>If our heart condemne us, God is greater then our heart, and knoweth all things,</hi> i.e. <hi>if our conſcience condemne us,</hi> then God will condemne us much more, but your Conſcience you ſay doth condemne you, and therefore your condition is very ſad before God. To give you ſatisfaction in this, I muſt confeſſe it is moſt true, that when <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> doth <hi>check, accuſe, condemne,</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon right information, there is no hope of avoiding the ſentence of God by any cloſe carriage by which we may thinke to ſhift and hide our ſelves and our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from his eyes. Yet this hinders not but that ſometimes the <hi>conſcience</hi> may <hi>condemne,</hi> where God <hi>doth not.</hi> For though it always <hi>judge for God,</hi> and on his ſide, yet it doth not alwaies <hi>judge with God,</hi> and according to his direction: but ſometimes it may be that with <hi>Jobs</hi> friends it makes a <hi>lye or God:</hi> and yet not purpoſely, but through miſinformation or prejudice, while it lookes on the worſt and not on the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:52020:83"/>beſt: that is to ſay on the preſent and particular <hi>indiſpoſition</hi> of the heart, and not on the ſincere and generall <hi>diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it. Such for want of better light in that particular <hi>may feare where no feare is,</hi> but let me tell ſuch they have a moſt gracious God, that takes no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſuch failings, but <hi>pardoneth and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſions of his people,</hi> as if he ſaw is not.<note place="margin">Mic. 7.18</note> Therefore let ſuch tender ones ſupport their ſpirits upon that ſweet and gracious promiſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſ. 42.3.</note> 
               <hi>not to breake the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax,</hi> i.e. God will not deale harſhly with ſuch weake and feeable ones; but ſupport and comfort them: for though their light be little and burne dimlie, yet the Lord will not extinguiſh it, but ſnuffe it and make it burne more cleerly.</p>
            <p>Conſider when your <hi>Conſcience</hi> doth <hi>accuſe,</hi> whether it proceed from ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>light</hi> out of the word of God, or from <hi>wrong information.</hi> If from <hi>light received</hi> out of the word of God, her ſentence is divine, and we are to regard it: but if otherwiſe upon <hi>wrong infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:52020:83"/>it is the error of <hi>conſcience,</hi> and our remedy is by ſending <hi>conſcience</hi> to ſeek the warrant of her ſentence out of the word of God.</p>
            <p>Againe if <hi>conſcience</hi> preſent unto you ſins which you committed many years agoe, and whereof you have repented. (For we are to know, that albeit after Repentance the Lord forgives the <hi>guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe</hi> of ſin, yet he will have the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> thereof to remaine in that conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faculty of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that it may both ſerve to humble us for the evill we have done, as alſo to preſerve us from ſin for the time to come.</p>
            <p>Againe if <hi>conſcience</hi> accuſe us for ſin committed and not repented, it is Gods great mercy, who by inward troubles wakens us to <hi>judge our ſelves</hi> here, that we may not be <hi>condemned</hi> of the Lord hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Now if any <hi>prophane Belialiſt</hi> ſhall at laſt ſay, what need all this adoe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a <hi>good conſcience:</hi> have not all men a <hi>good conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To ſuch I anſwer, in ſome ſence they
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:52020:84"/>have a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> namely a <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> which is <hi>metaphyſically</hi> and <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally good:</hi> and ſo they may and yet go to hell.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>conſcience</hi> that brings with it a <hi>continuall feaſt.</hi> and is accompanied with <hi>grace</hi> in this life, and <hi>glory</hi> in the life to come. It is more then <hi>metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> or <hi>naturally</hi> good. It is <hi>ſpiritually</hi> and <hi>ſupernaturally</hi> good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>conſcience purged and pacified</hi> by the bloud of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>conſcience</hi> habitually exerciſed to inoffenſiveneſſe <hi>both to God and man,</hi> Act. 24.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>conſcience</hi> that deſires to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly good <hi>in all things</hi> and <hi>alwaies,</hi> Act. 23.1.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A <hi>conſcience</hi> that will approve it ſelfe good even in the <hi>ſight of God,</hi> Act. 23.1. 1 Pet 3.21.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A <hi>conſcience</hi> that will give teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thy hearts <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and <hi>godly ſincerity,</hi> and ſopport thee under grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>troubles</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſes.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.8, 9.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Now if upon a ſerious ſearch, thou
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:52020:84"/>canſt evidence ſuch a <hi>conſcience,</hi> I muſt tell thee thou haſt obteined great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from the Lord, and art enriched with ſo rich a <hi>Iewell,</hi> that far ſurpaſſeth all the wealth of the world, and can never be worne by the men of this world. <hi>Rejoice</hi> therefore <hi>in the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies,</hi> and acquaint thy Chriſtian friends with it, that you may <hi>rejoice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> yea <hi>eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart for God hath accepted thee, Eccl.</hi> 9.7.</p>
            <p>The <hi>concluſion</hi> is this,<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> (<hi>Chriſtians</hi>) Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Conſciences</hi> are all <hi>obſcured, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and <hi>depraved</hi> through <hi>Adams</hi> fall. It is the part of every one to labour to reduce <hi>conſcience</hi> to its prime purity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. When a <hi>Compaſſe</hi> is out of frame we touch the <hi>needle</hi> of the Compaſſe with a <hi>Loadſtone,</hi> that the ſtone may draw it right to the <hi>Pole</hi> againe: So let our minds be touched with the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of the <hi>Spirit of grace,</hi> that they may come back to the Lord as to the Pole, and quiet themſelves in Chriſt as their <hi>true, ſole, and perfect Saviour.</hi> Let this be your daiely prayer unto
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:52020:85"/>God, and conſtant endeavour, who only can <hi>ſanctify us throughout in ſpirit, ſoule</hi> and <hi>body;</hi> who can make every <hi>part</hi> and <hi>member of our bodies,</hi> with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>power</hi> and <hi>faculty of our ſoules, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of Righteouſneſſe</hi> to doe him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>unto him that is able</hi> to make you to ſtand upright before him, and <hi>to keep you from falling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 24.25.</note> 
               <hi>and to preſent you faultleſſe before the preſence of his glory with exceeding joy, to the only Wiſe God our Saviour be Glory and Majeſty, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Power, now and for ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>April: 5th. 1656.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52020:85"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
